<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0" xmlns:itunes="http://www.itunes.com/dtds/podcast-1.0.dtd" xmlns:googleplay="http://www.google.com/schemas/play-podcasts/1.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Fabricated Knowledge]]></title><description><![CDATA[Let's learn more about the world's most important manufactured product. Meaningful insight, timely analysis, and an occasional investment idea. ]]></description><link>https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com</link><image><url>https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_256,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fac6587ae-db17-41fa-b25f-7dc0b7c601be_1000x1000.png</url><title>Fabricated Knowledge</title><link>https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com</link></image><generator>Substack</generator><lastBuildDate>Sun, 20 Mar 2022 13:30:55 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><copyright><![CDATA[mule]]></copyright><language><![CDATA[en]]></language><webMaster><![CDATA[doug@fabricatedknowledge.com]]></webMaster><itunes:owner><itunes:email><![CDATA[doug@fabricatedknowledge.com]]></itunes:email><itunes:name><![CDATA[Doug (mule)]]></itunes:name></itunes:owner><itunes:author><![CDATA[Doug (mule)]]></itunes:author><googleplay:owner><![CDATA[doug@fabricatedknowledge.com]]></googleplay:owner><googleplay:email><![CDATA[doug@fabricatedknowledge.com]]></googleplay:email><googleplay:author><![CDATA[Doug (mule)]]></googleplay:author><item><title><![CDATA[Weekly Update 3/15/2022]]></title><description><![CDATA[Update on Rambus, a Chinese delisting, and the most I've ever talked about Macro.]]></description><link>https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/weekly-update-3182022</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/weekly-update-3182022</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Doug (mule)]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 15 Mar 2022 12:03:28 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/h_600,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F9f4f42b9-9f57-49bf-8fe2-8c28f45e45e9_1155x445.png" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[
      <p>
          <a href="https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/weekly-update-3182022">
              Read more
          </a>
      </p>
   ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Ethereum 2.0 and GPUs & TSMC Monthly Revenue]]></title><description><![CDATA[It's actually happening this time. Plus TSMC monthly revenue beats!]]></description><link>https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/ethereum-20-and-gpus-and-tsmc-monthly</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/ethereum-20-and-gpus-and-tsmc-monthly</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Doug (mule)]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 10 Mar 2022 21:00:30 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/h_600,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F138686ec-d61b-4617-b27c-45a50550b526_1515x703.png" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[
      <p>
          <a href="https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/ethereum-20-and-gpus-and-tsmc-monthly">
              Read more
          </a>
      </p>
   ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Metrology Primer]]></title><description><![CDATA[The next of a series of primers in semicap manufacturing.]]></description><link>https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/metrology-primer</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/metrology-primer</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Doug (mule)]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 06 Mar 2022 17:00:36 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/h_600,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fe8d385b7-09f1-4d97-9e2c-8048dcb7fc0c_391x513.png" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I finally continue the <a href="https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/semiconductor-capital-equipment-series?s=w">Semicap Primer Series</a>! If you&#8217;ve been reading the newsletter at all as of late all I have been talking about is Metrology and Inspection. So, without further ado &#8211; let&#8217;s dive a bit deeper into what metrology and inspection mean.</p><p>As a quick reminder, Metrology and inspection are a meta-step in the fabrication process. Outside of patterning, deposition, etch, cleaning, metrology and inspection are the act of measuring the effectiveness of these previous steps. Inspection and Metrology are often called &#8220;process control&#8221;, and are a meta-process of quality control that is interwoven between all the process steps. </p><p>First by answering one of the hardest distinctions that I still get confused about and that is what exactly is the difference between the two?</p><h1>Metrology vs Inspection</h1><p>Metrology in its broadest sense of the word is the science of measurement and its application. In the case of semiconductors, <strong>it&#8217;s the science of measuring the wafer and critical dimensions of the chip to make sure it&#8217;s correct</strong>. It is a form of Process Control &#8211; a phrase used to talk about all kinds of measures taken by fabs to ensure uniformity, fewer mistakes, and the correct processes. Metrology is often a series of samples on the wafer to ensure that the manufacturing process is correct. This graphic by Hitachi Hi-Tech nails it. </p><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F6736327c-909c-4d1b-9308-155876c1be6c_1484x738.png"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F6736327c-909c-4d1b-9308-155876c1be6c_1484x738.png" width="1456" height="724" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/6736327c-909c-4d1b-9308-155876c1be6c_1484x738.png&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:724,&quot;width&quot;:1456,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:396809,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt=""></a><figcaption class="image-caption"><a href="https://www.hitachi-hightech.com/global/products/device/semiconductor/metrology-inspection.html">https://www.hitachi-hightech.com/global/products/device/semiconductor/metrology-inspection.html</a></figcaption></figure></div><p>Most of these are measurements to check to see this semiconductor is working as it should be. Now let&#8217;s move on to the very similar but slightly different category of inspection.</p><p><strong>Inspection is using devices to inspect wafers and masks for defects. </strong>The two are so confusing because well Inspection is another form of process control and similar to metrology. However, in this case, it is in the form of looking actively over the wafer and <strong>finding results.</strong> Metrology is a passive result quality control method, akin to measuring a dimension for variance. Inspection is actively looking for things with a fine-tooth comb &#8211; trying to find exactly where the defect lies and why. </p><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F1a7a4566-1698-487c-8c22-60968ab2d4af_1576x970.png"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F1a7a4566-1698-487c-8c22-60968ab2d4af_1576x970.png" width="1456" height="896" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/1a7a4566-1698-487c-8c22-60968ab2d4af_1576x970.png&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:896,&quot;width&quot;:1456,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:780404,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt=""></a></figure></div><p>When comparing the two I really think my favorite analogy is calling metrology a routine police patrol while an inspection is more akin to investigating the scene of a crime and looking for the murder weapon.</p><p>So in this analogy metrology is trying to stop routine but common mistakes from happening. This is mostly done by comparing the expected result of a peaceful neighborhood to the actual neighborhood. These kinds of routine patrols prevent persistent crime (or defects) to creep into day-to-day life. Inspection is a much finer process of looking at what exactly caused what. Both are obviously important in the process of day-to-day defect management. &nbsp;</p><h1>Why Metrology and Inspection Should Do Well</h1><p>I wrote a lot more about this in &#8220;Rising Cost of a Semiconductor&#8221; &#8211; in particular, that the yield math is one of the most compelling arguments for the need for more metrology. The cost of defect failures is starting to spiral out of control, and the cheapest insurance against this is more Metrology and Inspection. One of the changes the industry is adopting is <strong>advanced packaging</strong> as the primary driver to increasing semiconductor performance. The push to advanced packaging has an entire set of consequences, namely newer packaging technology and a new vector of failure.</p><p>Additionally, <strong>Metrology and Inspection spending tends to ramp before the rest of the tools, and that is why they should continue to grow so robustly in 2022 given that large fabs are just starting to come online</strong>. Metrology and inspection ramps are likely happening currently for the N3 and N5 nodes at TSMC and Intel. </p><p>In my view, there are two drivers of metrology and inspection intensity increasing. The first is that leading-edge processes continue to be demanding and the cost of failure is very high. This should at least grow with WFE. The second is the rise of increasing complexity in the backend driven by advanced packaging, and this should grow faster than WFE.</p><h2>Front End Metrology </h2><p>Metrology intensity rises for the most part in-line with the number of steps of a semiconductor. That is to say that metrology intensity is likely going to rise in line with semicap intensity. Metrology and process control is, unfortunately, an insurance product, and is only bought when yields become increasingly hard. Given the increasing complexity of semiconductor manufacturing, it makes sense that metrology and inspection should rise at least as much as the other areas of semicap. </p><p>I love this slide from KLAC. The margin of error is very low. This slide from KLA points out that a 99.5% rate of success would be a complete failure after the ~1000 non-metrology steps needed to make a modern semiconductor. Essentially the manufacturing process requires perfection.   </p><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fea6fd828-cc20-40d5-bea3-d40606932ced_1312x658.png"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fea6fd828-cc20-40d5-bea3-d40606932ced_1312x658.png" width="1312" height="658" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/ea6fd828-cc20-40d5-bea3-d40606932ced_1312x658.png&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:658,&quot;width&quot;:1312,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:494047,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt=""></a></figure></div><p>Given that the increasing number of steps and complexity is a trend that will not be stopping, <strong>metrology should increase in-line or possibly a bit more as yield challenges make ramping more complex nodes harder.</strong> The real kicker for increasing complexity in my opinion is more on the backend, where the density of pitches and cost of failure is spiraling out of control. The risk of a large and expensive finished good failing because of relatively cheap packaging technology is making the cost of insurance rise steeply. </p><h2>Back End Metrology</h2><p>Advanced packaging is of course the big focus area for semiconductors. Each of the new techniques such as fine pitch flip-chip, fan-out wafer-level packaging, and  hybrid bonding are additive to the manufacturing process. (<a href="https://semianalysis.substack.com/p/advanced-packaging-part-1-pad-limited">For a very good and recent primer written about the types of Advanced Packaging refer to Dylan&#8217;s latest series</a>). </p><p>These costs are additive to making a semiconductor and extend beyond just the traditional front-end processes. This is additive to the total cost of making a semiconductor package. The problem lies when you have an expensive piece of semi-finished goods being bonded together in increasingly expensive processes that require precision. The precision for metrology and inspection is increasing and that demand is moving metrology demand higher. </p><p>The cost of 1 expensive die in a multi-chip module failing because of a relatively cheap misplaced micro-bump could ruin the entire package, and this is why the cost of failure is increasing and thus &#8220;insurance&#8221; of metrology and inspection is rising in the BOEL (Back end of line). In addition to the logic of &#8220;insurance&#8221; being important, the entire category is one of the largest incremental growth categories within the entire semiconductor fabrication process.</p><p>Advanced Packaging is a huge catalyst for more Process Control, and for once I believe that Metrology is going from a &#8220;nice to have&#8221; and cost center to a strategic focus in the front end. A pretty simple illustration of the impact of effective yield per chiplet shows a pretty startling impact of the yield &#8211; it&#8217;s going to have to be higher for an effective yield to be acceptable. Note the similarity to the previous slide from KLA.</p><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffe29c464-7ae7-463c-b600-1d0692fca468_554x243.png"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffe29c464-7ae7-463c-b600-1d0692fca468_554x243.png" width="554" height="243" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/fe29c464-7ae7-463c-b600-1d0692fca468_554x243.png&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:243,&quot;width&quot;:554,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:38714,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt=""></a></figure></div><h1>Technical Dive</h1><p>Okay after explaining to you at a high level about metrology &#8211; I want to take a bit of a deeper dive. If you want to skip this and go to the company overviews I fully understand &#8211; this is primarily if you want to learn a bit more about how and why metrology and inspection work.&nbsp;</p><p>I want to preface that most of this is a lagging edge from a <a href="https://smile.amazon.com/Handbook-Silicon-Semiconductor-Metrology-Diebold/dp/0824705068?sa-no-redirect=1">2000 era textbook</a>. In interviews and conversations with experts, I&#8217;ve gotten that most of these core assumptions have stayed the same but are just operating on a smaller scale &#8211; so let&#8217;s explain some of the major steps in the metrology and inspection process. </p><p>At a high level, all of inspection and metrology can be simplified as a source of electrons, X-rays, or light hitting a sample and then collecting either secondary electrons, x-rays, or other data from that interaction. That is the core technique of metrology and inspection. Some of the light or electrons pass through, some are bounced off the surface. The information collected from these secondary results can tell a meaningful amount of the sample. This is the core mechanic of both inspection and metrology processes.</p><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fe8d385b7-09f1-4d97-9e2c-8048dcb7fc0c_391x513.png"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fe8d385b7-09f1-4d97-9e2c-8048dcb7fc0c_391x513.png" width="391" height="513" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/e8d385b7-09f1-4d97-9e2c-8048dcb7fc0c_391x513.png&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:513,&quot;width&quot;:391,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:86640,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt=""></a></figure></div><p>This is a core graphic. First notice the beam sources (TEM, HREM, SEM, STEM, FIB, HeIM) creating secondary electrons, x-rays, or other secondary particles that can be measured. The interaction effects of these particles with the sample create a large amount of information that can be used to then create inferences about the dimension, material, and other properties of the sample. </p><p>The raw data from this process however is not enough to understand what an engineer is looking at, it actually takes a large amount of model-based simulation and experimentation to create a model that then better reflects reality. In my estimation, there is a meaningful cumulative advantage from creating solutions in metrology because it isn&#8217;t just the physical tools but the models of reality itself in conjunction that creates the solution. Creating the model from scratch takes a lot of effort, data, time series, and other factors for various methods of metrology and inspection. </p><p>Now next there are different times metrology and inspection are used. <strong>In-situ versus standalone</strong>. Both have their places, but I would say the difference is that in-situ is within a series of chambers or part of the chamber process, while standalone is a separate machine that is larger and more accurate. In a perfect world, everything would be in-situ, but the reality is that standalone machines are needed. </p><p><strong>In-situ</strong> - &#8220;In process&#8221;, and often used to improve the performance of a chamber or step. Think of this as double-checking your work on the fly. </p><p><strong>Standalone Metrology/Inspection - </strong>This is a standalone machine. The reason for standalone machines is that the stage, angle, precision, and throughput are much better in a standalone process. It makes sense to separate the processes as some of the processes can be messy or even destructive. </p><h2>Ebeam or Not to Ebeam</h2><p>Another area I want to talk about is Ebeam versus optical. Ebeam is a process of pushing primary electrons towards a wafer in a tight beam, hence an electron beam. This ebeam process creates secondary electrons and backscattered electrons. Secondary electrons are measured from the same side as the beam and are sensitive to the surface, while backscattered electrons are measured on the backside. Secondary electrons are better at surface information, while back scattered electrons tell more information about the composition of the sample. </p><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F522a9bfe-532f-49f2-b6e0-0d9947e310e3_1241x608.png"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F522a9bfe-532f-49f2-b6e0-0d9947e310e3_1241x608.png" width="1241" height="608" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/522a9bfe-532f-49f2-b6e0-0d9947e310e3_1241x608.png&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:608,&quot;width&quot;:1241,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:227410,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt=""></a></figure></div><p>The net effect is a high-resolution image-based inspection method. This works to resolution levels lower than optical methods and importantly has a roadmap to scale. The only real problem is throughput, as ebeam is a focused beam with lower throughput and higher resolution. </p><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F73fd9c9d-7a2e-4e38-aa00-d6856ac74d3d_1589x652.png"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F73fd9c9d-7a2e-4e38-aa00-d6856ac74d3d_1589x652.png" width="1456" height="597" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/73fd9c9d-7a2e-4e38-aa00-d6856ac74d3d_1589x652.png&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:597,&quot;width&quot;:1456,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:500145,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt=""></a></figure></div><p>The part that would make Ebeam more competitive is throughput increases. This is currently being worked on by Applied, KLAC, and ASML. However ebeam is still orders of magnitude behind. </p><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F8f2580f4-aed5-460b-a3f2-e445c7e4e3e6_844x476.png"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F8f2580f4-aed5-460b-a3f2-e445c7e4e3e6_844x476.png" width="844" height="476" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/8f2580f4-aed5-460b-a3f2-e445c7e4e3e6_844x476.png&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:476,&quot;width&quot;:844,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:135090,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt=""></a></figure></div><p>Recent throughput increases by the likes of Applied Materials have managed to increase throughput, but Ebeam still is orders of magnitude behind Optical inspection. Ebeam adoption will increase regardless, as the resolution offered will matter for 3nm and below. </p><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fa7deb801-d6e5-45e1-8342-6dbb3590d573_1647x693.png"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fa7deb801-d6e5-45e1-8342-6dbb3590d573_1647x693.png" width="1456" height="613" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/a7deb801-d6e5-45e1-8342-6dbb3590d573_1647x693.png&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:613,&quot;width&quot;:1456,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:1107649,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt=""></a></figure></div><p>However, the reality I&#8217;ve come to realize is that Ebeam and Optical are both going to exist for a long time. There is a direct complementary aspect of optical. Optical in particular is well suited for wafer to wafer variation and systematic defects, aka Metrology. While Ebeam is going to be a larger portion of inspection for leading-edge sub 7nm logic. </p><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fe1760a1a-bf73-4010-a76e-cbc41be6032d_850x467.png"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fe1760a1a-bf73-4010-a76e-cbc41be6032d_850x467.png" width="850" height="467" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/e1760a1a-bf73-4010-a76e-cbc41be6032d_850x467.png&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:467,&quot;width&quot;:850,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:344045,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt=""></a></figure></div><p>One of the big takeaways is that while Ebeam is clearly a runaway growth category in the short term as it creates a larger addressable market, however, it doesn&#8217;t come at the expense of optical strictly. Optical inspection is likely going to be used less, but Optical itself is not going away. Both are just different tools, and both are in high demand as scaling becomes harder. </p><h2>Optical is Not Constrained in Metrology</h2><p>The last thing I want to talk about is the misnomer of the limitations of optical technology. When I started this dive I was under the assumption due to the size of the pitches optical technology was going to start hitting the wall of the light being larger than the feature the machine was inspecting.</p><p>This is not a limitation as I first thought. The primary reason for this is scatterometry, which is measuring the trajectory and polarization of light after it hits a surface. Think of modern optical techniques as bouncing light off a surface and measuring the angle of light scattering to create inferences about the sample. </p><p>By systematically bombarding a surface with optical light you can find a lot of information about the underlying, even if the sample is larger than the light source you&#8217;re bombarding the sample with. That is the modern state of optical, and it seems like this can scale for a meaningful while yet at an extremely cost-effective rate with higher throughput. Importantly this method is model-based, meaning that the bouncing of the lights has to be interpolated with a meaningful amount of data and modeling experience. There is a cumulative advantage here, as entrants in optical model-based inspection seem unlikely. </p><p>In particular when a large percentage of the sample has to be measured optical really shines. In this case, Metrology will likely be optical-based for a long time yet, while inspection will continue to pursue ebeam and other non-optical-based methods. </p><h2>Overview of Types of Metrology and Inspection</h2><p>Now I want to start to move onto the common &#8220;types&#8221; of metrology and inspection. The thing I want to focus on is that while each has specific applications they are often used for, the reality is multiple methods can achieve the same results. Oftentimes choosing between a CD-SEM and OCD film techniques doesn&#8217;t really matter, because both are good enough for the job. The choice and trade off for why each technique gets selected is something process engineers decide, based on the risks and benefits of each type process.   </p><p>First let&#8217;s start with the original inspection and metrology method, CD-SEM. </p><ul><li><p>CD-SEM - Critical Dimension Scanning Electron Microscope</p></li></ul><p>CD-SEM is an electron beam that is scanned onto the surface of a wafer and the interaction of the measurement of the surface topology generates data that gives information about the materials. </p><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F8ba819a4-6864-46fe-8ed9-596edf24ff19_444x320.jpeg"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F8ba819a4-6864-46fe-8ed9-596edf24ff19_444x320.jpeg" width="444" height="320" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/8ba819a4-6864-46fe-8ed9-596edf24ff19_444x320.jpeg&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:320,&quot;width&quot;:444,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:&quot;Scanning Electron Microscope schematic&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt="Scanning Electron Microscope schematic" title="Scanning Electron Microscope schematic"></a></figure></div><p>It&#8217;s important to note that SEM is not a camera but a beam that creates information about a surface and then is collected. When these electrons interact with a sample it creates multiple electrons as a result which can then be measured and create an image. CD-SEM is one of the most common forms of inspection and metrology. </p><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fa2d79991-a5cb-4876-b9e8-becf15da4a5a_400x400.png"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fa2d79991-a5cb-4876-b9e8-becf15da4a5a_400x400.png" width="400" height="400" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/a2d79991-a5cb-4876-b9e8-becf15da4a5a_400x400.png&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:400,&quot;width&quot;:400,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:&quot;Electron beam interaction schematic&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt="Electron beam interaction schematic" title="Electron beam interaction schematic"></a></figure></div><ul><li><p>TEM - Transmission electron microscope</p></li></ul><p>A transmission electron microscope is similar to CD-SEM, but is more focused on transmitted electrons that pass through a sample to create an image. This obviously is useful to create multi-layer deep images for semiconductor manufacturing. TEM and SEM can be used in conjunction to become STEM. One of the bigger problems with TEM is the field of view can be limited, as well as the interaction between SEM and TEM can create noise. </p><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F58828ec8-804c-4a5a-a18f-411574c3c915_1344x607.png"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F58828ec8-804c-4a5a-a18f-411574c3c915_1344x607.png" width="1344" height="607" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/58828ec8-804c-4a5a-a18f-411574c3c915_1344x607.png&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:607,&quot;width&quot;:1344,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:48776,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt=""></a><figcaption class="image-caption"><a href="https://www.thermofisher.com/us/en/home/materials-science/learning-center/applications/sem-tem-difference.html#:~:text=The%20main%20difference%20between%20SEM,sample)%20to%20create%20an%20image.">Source</a></figcaption></figure></div><ul><li><p><a href="https://www.horiba.com/gbr/products/by-technique/molecular-spectroscopy/photoluminescence-pl-electroluminescence-el/#:~:text=Photoluminescence%20spectroscopy%2C%20often%20referred%20to,nondestructive%20method%20of%20probing%20materials.&amp;text=Photoluminescence%20used%20in%20Fluorescence%20spectroscopy,two%20results%3A%20Fluorescence%20and%20Phosphorescence.">Photoluminescence Spectroscopy</a></p></li></ul><p>This is a method of directing light on a sample and measuring photo-excitation. By adding light to the sample, the material can jump to higher electronic states and release photons. This can give insight into the optoelectronic properties of semiconductors and is a measure of the outer orbitals of a material&#8217;s electrons. </p><ul><li><p><a href="https://www.rigaku.com/techniques/x-ray-diffraction-xrd">X-RAY Diffraction</a> (XRD)</p></li></ul><p>This is a method to measure the three-dimensional structure of a semiconductor. It&#8217;s used to measure the atomic structures of crystal structure and is thus helpful for semiconductor manufacturing metrology. <strong>It&#8217;s primarily used for materials metrology</strong>.</p><ul><li><p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/X-ray_fluorescence">X-RAY Fluorescence</a> (XRF)</p></li></ul><p>This is another material and chemical metrology process. After the bombardment of high-energy x-ray, the secondary x-ray expels electrons that can be used to create information about their underlying composition. <strong>Again for materials metrology</strong>. </p><ul><li><p><a href="https://www.malvernpanalytical.com/en/products/technology/xray-analysis/xray-scattering/x-ray-reflectometery#:~:text=X%2Dray%20reflectometry%20(XRR)%20is%20an%20analytical%20technique%20for,external%20reflection%20of%20X%2Drays.&amp;text=In%20reflectivity%20experiments%2C%20the%20X,measured%20around%20the%20critical%20angle.">X-RAY Reflectometry (XRR)</a></p></li></ul><p>XRR focuses on the amount of reflection of X-ray beams from a high-energy source.  Reflectometry can be used to characterize structures in the semiconductor manufacturing process. Hint once again another materials metrology product. </p><ul><li><p><a href="https://www.novami.com/nova-technology/x-ray-photospectroscopy-xps/">X-RAY Spectrometry</a></p></li></ul><p>XPS spectra are obtained by exposing the film of interest to a primary x-ray which can either be absorbed by the material or scattered through the material. If the x-ray is energetic enough, it is absorbed and transfers energy to an inner shell electron. The electrons emitted because of this incident x-ray will have kinetic energy that is representative of the chemical signature of the element. Analysis of this photoelectric effect is known as XPS. (This is straight from the Nova Instruments website)</p><ul><li><p><a href="https://www.gatewayanalytical.com/resources/publications/comparison-raman-and-ftir-spectroscopy-advantages-and-limitations/">Raman Spectroscopy</a></p></li></ul><p>This is primarily a process of light scattering. By measuring the scattering of light you can find a fingerprint of the underlying materials and chemical composition. Raman measures the change of polarization of light to find characteristics such as strain, crystallinity, phases, grain size, and composition. This is a non-destructive and optical process. </p><ul><li><p><a href="https://www.thermofisher.com/us/en/home/industrial/spectroscopy-elemental-isotope-analysis/spectroscopy-elemental-isotope-analysis-learning-center/molecular-spectroscopy-information/ftir-information/ftir-basics.html">FTIR Spectroscopy</a></p></li></ul><p>FTIR or Fourier transform infrared spectroscopy relies on Infrared light instead. By measuring the reflection and absorption of light you can find the frequency that is associated with each chemical bond. This is a complementary process to Raman Spectroscopy. </p><ul><li><p><a href="https://semilab.com/category/products/model-based-infrared-reflectometry#:~:text=Model%2DBased%20Infrared%20Reflectometry%20is,destructive%20measurements%20on%20process%20wafers.">Model-based infrared reflectometry</a></p></li></ul><p>An optical method for thin-film measurements. MBIR is importantly model-based and uses infrared light instead of other visible spectrum light to create measurements. </p><ul><li><p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ellipsometry">Spectroscopic Ellisopmeter</a></p></li></ul><p>Not a specific method, but rather an optical tool that is used to find the dielectric properties of a film. An ellipsometer emits light, polarizes it, and after the beam is reflected from the surface it measures the polarization of light. This is an indirect method. </p><ul><li><p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Focused_ion_beam">Focused Ion Beam (FIB)</a></p></li></ul><p>Focused Ion Beams is similar to a scanning electron beam but rather than a large light source it uses an extremely focused beam of ions. Since the beam of ions are focused, it hits the surface and sputters a </p><ul><li><p><a href="https://ontoinnovation.com/writable/files/Resources/OCD-metrology-for-semiconductor-manufacturing_VTC_Sept21.pdf">Optical CD (Critical Dimension)</a></p></li></ul><p>Optical CD is based on scatterometry-based OCD to provide 3-D information to characterize structures. By shining a light on a film and measuring the scattered light and polarization, OCD can characterize the structure on a very cost-efficient basis. </p><ul><li><p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Atomic_force_microscopy">CD AFM - Critical Dimension Atomic Force Microscopes</a></p></li></ul><p>Important to note that Atomic Force Microscope is a destructive process. AFM drags a probe across the surface of a sample and then measures the debris and other products that sputter off the face of the product. This is a destructive practice so it&#8217;s mostly used in scaling process but not for high volume manufacturing.</p><ul><li><p>Laser Acoustic</p></li></ul><p>This is an interesting and niche metrology tool. Primarily through the Metapulse tool (Onto), you ping a sample with a laser and then measure the acoustic vibration of the material using sensors. This is used for metal composition metrology. </p><ul><li><p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Electron_backscatter_diffraction">Electron Backscatter Diffraction</a></p></li></ul><p>This is how an inspection can &#8220;see-through&#8221; a sample. When a surface is bombarded with electrons, some electrons slip through orbitals and inevitably penetrate a sample and come out the backside of the sample. This is backscatter diffraction, and by collecting this information you can create information about the sample&#8217;s crystalline structure. </p><h2>Conclusions</h2><p>Sadly this is not an exhaustive list of the entire processes used for metrology and inspection. I wanted to introduce you to some of the most basic forms of inspection and metrology and open your eyes to the variety and types of meta-information created from each source of light, x-ray, infrared light, or electron beam. </p><p>The primary problem is that many tools actually use multiple techniques in conjunction to create solutions that fit the exact use case of the semiconductor production step. <strong>For example for measuring a thin film, both CD-SEM and OCD work, but one or another gets chosen depending on the process and tool qualities</strong>. Put differently there are many different sets of tools that can do the same job, and it&#8217;s the job of the companies themselves to bring the best solution to solve the problem at hand. </p><p>Even Ebeam, the notorious disruptor technology will not &#8220;kill&#8221; optical, just widen the breadth of tools that a process engineer has at their disposal. </p><p>For more analysis on specific company product portfolios and what each public company is levered to, as well as an almost exhaustive list of metrology tools, refer to the rest of the section behind the paywall. </p><p class="button-wrapper" data-attrs="{&quot;url&quot;:&quot;https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/subscribe?&quot;,&quot;text&quot;:&quot;Subscribe now&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:null,&quot;class&quot;:null}"><a class="button primary" href="https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/subscribe?"><span>Subscribe now</span></a></p>
      <p>
          <a href="https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/metrology-primer">
              Read more
          </a>
      </p>
   ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Intel's Investor Day - Nothing New]]></title><description><![CDATA[Some thoughts on the financials for Intel's day, and thoughts on the political climate.]]></description><link>https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/intels-investor-day-nothing-new</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/intels-investor-day-nothing-new</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Doug (mule)]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 25 Feb 2022 17:24:18 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://cdn.substack.com/image/youtube/w_728,c_limit/KByyChZj064" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Pssst. Dylan of Semianalysis and I had a great podcast about Intel Investor Day.  <a href="https://anchor.fm/doug-dylan/episodes/Episode-2-Intels-Investor-Day-e1en164">Check it out!</a> I want to apologize for getting this out so late as well, I meant to send it on Tuesday but sickness kind of stopped that. Enjoy! </p><div><hr></div><p>Intel&#8217;s big investor day was anything but big. The stock reacted poorly, down 5% on a day that was a widespread sell-off anyways. </p><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbe32664a-cc3a-41e2-8898-d1a1ba57daf1_2400x1240.png"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbe32664a-cc3a-41e2-8898-d1a1ba57daf1_2400x1240.png" width="1456" height="752" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/be32664a-cc3a-41e2-8898-d1a1ba57daf1_2400x1240.png&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:752,&quot;width&quot;:1456,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt=""></a></figure></div><p>I want to briefly summarize what matters for the stock. There was very little incremental news to the technology roadmap, and the financial outlook was underwhelming, to say the least. </p><p>The revenue guide was low single-digit growth, transitioning to mid-single-digit growth, to then double-digit growth in 2026. </p><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fdf6c746d-34db-4ffa-928f-c29e3e0c8013_1432x808.png"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fdf6c746d-34db-4ffa-928f-c29e3e0c8013_1432x808.png" width="1432" height="808" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/df6c746d-34db-4ffa-928f-c29e3e0c8013_1432x808.png&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:808,&quot;width&quot;:1432,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:253178,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt=""></a></figure></div><p>They expect to improve gross margins when they get leadership products. They provided this simple bridge. David Zinsner (the new CFO) reiterated multiple times he thinks that this gross margin bridge was conservative. </p><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F4c7e6171-b41b-4376-a04b-13a334ae7e4b_1519x811.png"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F4c7e6171-b41b-4376-a04b-13a334ae7e4b_1519x811.png" width="1456" height="777" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/4c7e6171-b41b-4376-a04b-13a334ae7e4b_1519x811.png&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:777,&quot;width&quot;:1456,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:430549,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt=""></a></figure></div><p>The real meat of the financial outlook was given in a two-part long-term model. First, is the investment phase model, where they spend heavily to catch up to the industry and bootstrap their foundry business. </p><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fca6ee5b9-ba6b-4fd7-8f8c-ea8a3fe7cb5a_1496x836.png"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fca6ee5b9-ba6b-4fd7-8f8c-ea8a3fe7cb5a_1496x836.png" width="1456" height="814" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/ca6ee5b9-ba6b-4fd7-8f8c-ea8a3fe7cb5a_1496x836.png&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:814,&quot;width&quot;:1456,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:422268,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt=""></a></figure></div><p>And then the longer-term model, when Intel presumably is back in the lead during their fateful 2024 crossover timeline. 2024 is when Pat Gelsinger believes they can take process leadership, and have better revenue growth and margins. </p><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F892a3919-814d-4da3-a163-c603a78b69a7_1431x827.png"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F892a3919-814d-4da3-a163-c603a78b69a7_1431x827.png" width="1431" height="827" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/892a3919-814d-4da3-a163-c603a78b69a7_1431x827.png&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:827,&quot;width&quot;:1431,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:369258,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt=""></a></figure></div><p>The thing is that the total vision was pretty underwhelming if you ask me. The reason why? Well, it&#8217;s consensus already. </p><h2>It&#8217;s Consensus Already</h2><p>One of the things that frustrated me is that I believe that the gross margin and revenue goals from the analyst day were within 50 bps of street consensus until 2025, and this is why the market found this model so particularly uncompelling. This is what we expected already, and stating it again felt pointless. This comment in particular was extremely off-putting as well.</p><blockquote><p>&#8220;I want to double the earnings and <strong>double the multiple of this company</strong>&#8221;. </p></blockquote><div id="youtube2-KByyChZj064" class="youtube-wrap" data-attrs="{&quot;videoId&quot;:&quot;KByyChZj064&quot;,&quot;startTime&quot;:&quot;3826&quot;,&quot;endTime&quot;:null}"><iframe src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/KByyChZj064?start=3826&amp;rel=0&amp;autoplay=0&amp;showinfo=0&amp;enablejsapi=0" frameborder="0" loading="lazy" gesture="media" allow="autoplay; fullscreen" allowautoplay="true" allowfullscreen="true" width="728" height="409"></iframe></div><p>Historically commenting on the multiple is pretty icky if you ask me. Also if you compare it to the historical multiple it feels pretty unlikely. Will Intel really trade at 28x forward earnings? </p><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff709170b-2e81-4bea-a214-2edf57c51a2b_2400x1240.png"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff709170b-2e81-4bea-a214-2edf57c51a2b_2400x1240.png" width="1456" height="752" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/f709170b-2e81-4bea-a214-2edf57c51a2b_2400x1240.png&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:752,&quot;width&quot;:1456,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt=""></a></figure></div><p>Trading at 20x forward earnings would put it in a multiple class Intel hasn&#8217;t seen since pre-2008. Albeit growing double digits would also be something Intel hasn&#8217;t done since 2018 (~13% YoY revenue growth) and hasn&#8217;t done for a period of 3 consecutive years in a row since 2003-2005. There has to be a lot fundamentally different for Intel to deserve that doubling in multiple. We will talk about the doubling in earnings a bit. </p><h2>Financial Model &amp; Free Cash Flow Levers</h2><p>The thing that also is a bit frustrating is looking at this company on an earnings basis when they guided for 3 years of flat to negative FCF. Here is my model backing out of their long-term guidance. </p><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F44716cdd-8d16-4139-8a01-08ae5d319167_617x664.png"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F44716cdd-8d16-4139-8a01-08ae5d319167_617x664.png" width="617" height="664" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/44716cdd-8d16-4139-8a01-08ae5d319167_617x664.png&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:664,&quot;width&quot;:617,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:43104,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt=""></a><figcaption class="image-caption">Notice doubling earnings from the 2022 level, not the 2021 level. For simplicity&#8217;s sake, I took the top end of their ranges. The conservatism that David and Pat stress I think is reflected by me assuming share count doesn&#8217;t grow. </figcaption></figure></div><p>So while it trades at &#8220;just 10x 2024 earnings&#8221; it will make no FCF in that year. There is so much implied in the model for the huge technical and financial turnaround in 2024. Everything in the model hinges on 2024 which is a few years away and implies a huge margin acceleration. From 0% FCF margin to 20% in 2 years, this seems unlikely.</p><p>The only thing that really made me believe this is possible is if they play the government incentives game really hard. Their initial capex guidance is based on 10% savings from net spend (their guide) to gross. </p><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F6506e5b6-994d-4e8f-9fb6-af9d971d6828_622x523.png"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F6506e5b6-994d-4e8f-9fb6-af9d971d6828_622x523.png" width="622" height="523" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/6506e5b6-994d-4e8f-9fb6-af9d971d6828_622x523.png&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:523,&quot;width&quot;:622,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:43076,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt=""></a></figure></div><p>David Zinser also thinks that a 30% cost reduction number seems like the number they will get and would be &#8220;surprised&#8221; if Intel didn&#8217;t there.</p><p>So from my reading of this situation, Intel could hit the FCF number if they bag the entire savings from a 10% cost reduction to a 30% cost reduction, and then improve total EBIT margins by 800 bps. I think at least 1/3rd of the FCF bridge will be driven by playing around with the net and gross capex assumptions. Pretty heroic assumptions, which brings me to the entire crux of the investor day. We are waiting for 2024. </p><h2>Waiting for Gadot (aka 2024)</h2><p>The Intel turnaround is waiting for 2024. We kind of already knew that now we just have financial clarity until that fateful year. The financials were as bad as we expected, and for an Investor day, there was almost no surprise. </p><p>Another thing that I keep coming back to is that everyone expects that Intel&#8217;s turnaround will mean some drastic and amazing returns for the stock. To be clear if the turnaround happens with no hitches I think that the stock could easily do a 20%+ CAGR to 2026, but I also think that can be said of multiple companies in the semiconductor space at these current prices. I think the problem is that most investors are mentally comparing Intel to their notable competitor: AMD.</p><p>I want to be clear, this is not AMD. AMD went from almost no share to meaningful amounts of share and massively improved their economics in that time period. <strong>The torque of 10% to 40% share and 20% gross margins to 50% margins will not be repeated</strong>. The best case for Intel I think is something that is a 20%+ CAGR, or a rough tripling. That&#8217;s a great return! But I want to say this is the BEST CASE and is still contingent on a meaningful amount of execution risk and zero FCF for multiple years along the way. Investor day didn&#8217;t really give us much hope other than to wait until 2024. </p><p><strong>We are still just waiting for 2024 to see the process leadership be regained.</strong></p><div><hr></div><p>Also, it looks like the crux of what I said about <a href="https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/tower-semi-buyout-tips-intels-hand?utm_source=url">Tower tipping their hand of Intel becoming a holding company seems true</a>. </p><blockquote><p>The other thing I&#8217;ve said is that, &#8220;Hey, I&#8217;d like to do a Mobileye-like spin on our foundry business at some point as well.&#8221; I&#8217;m going to keep the structure, as opposed to integrating as much, I&#8217;m going to keep it more separate to enable that, which means I&#8217;m going to leverage a lot more of Tower and the expertise that it builds over time as part of it.</p></blockquote><p><a href="https://stratechery.com/2022/an-interview-with-intel-ceo-pat-gelsinger/">Ala the venerable Stratechery</a>. </p><p>The screenshots from above are from a very simplistic model that I used to replicate the investor day goals. It is behind the paywall for paying subscribers only. Feel free to mess with the assumptions yourself. The FCF part of the model is disconnected from earnings, mostly because of how meaningful the D&amp;A cost ramp will be for the next few years. </p>
      <p>
          <a href="https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/intels-investor-day-nothing-new">
              Read more
          </a>
      </p>
   ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Quick Earnings Round Up 2/18/2022]]></title><description><![CDATA[A short round - ASE & AMKR, NVDA, AMAT, and SMIC]]></description><link>https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/quick-earnings-round-up-2182022</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/quick-earnings-round-up-2182022</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Doug (mule)]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 21 Feb 2022 17:53:00 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/h_600,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F57c67378-2739-49d8-bc41-881ed2440a09_1336x854.png" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[
      <p>
          <a href="https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/quick-earnings-round-up-2182022">
              Read more
          </a>
      </p>
   ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Tower Semi Buyout Tips Intel's Hand]]></title><description><![CDATA[The rationale behind the Tower Semi acquisition and things to watch out for at Intel's investor day]]></description><link>https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/tower-semi-buyout-tips-intels-hand</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/tower-semi-buyout-tips-intels-hand</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Doug (mule)]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 17 Feb 2022 15:35:36 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/h_600,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F65f3112b-f836-433b-8a49-3dc7cb53a62d_1344x1396.png" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2>Intel bids for Tower Semi</h2><p>First I have to quote myself because Tower was an error of omission. <a href="https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/the-rising-tide-of-semiconductor?r=qq5">In November in a piece that was likely too long for its own good</a>, I mentioned that trailing edge fabs are in a huge position of strength and even called out Tower Semi.</p><blockquote><p><strong>A name that I think is worth looking into, but I don&#8217;t really have the bandwidth for at this moment, is Tower Semi</strong>. It screams like a strategic asset, and all they&#8217;ve been doing for the last 10 years is buying lagging-edge fabs. Keep an eye on that, but for now I still think these aren&#8217;t as attractive as just metrology companies in Semicap.</p></blockquote><p>First I think it&#8217;s funny because semicap has only gone down since then, and Tower Semi of course got a nearly 50% premium bid. So let&#8217;s dive a bit deeper into why Tower Semi is such a strategic asset and why Intel is buying them right now. Let&#8217;s start with a brief history of Tower Semi.</p><h2>Tower Semi - The Fab Partner</h2><p>Tower Semiconductor&#8217;s (formerly TowerJazz) history is a storied one. The beginning of Tower starts in 1993 with National Semiconductor&#8217;s divestiture of its Israeli fab in Migdal Haemek, Israel. Tower expanded its Israeli footprint with Fab 2 alongside Fab 1 in 2001.</p><p>The real transformational deal that made Tower into who they are today was an all-stock merger with Jazz semiconductor in 2008. Jazz semiconductor actually started as a subsidiary of Conexant and was funded by the Carlyle group. Jazz was taken public by a blank check company (SPAC!) and their fab is the Newport Beach fab. </p><p>The next big win was a Panasonic JV that enabled Tower to launch 3 Japanese fabs with Panasonic as the main customer and 49% owner. This JV helped Tower offer 65nm CMOS and 300mm technologies for the first time. </p><p>In 2016 they acquired another fab with the purchase of Maxim Integrated&#8217;s San Antonio fab. This was a way to offload the Maxim fab to transition to a fab-lite model and helped expand production of 200mm wafers for Tower. </p><p>Last but not least is the Agrate Italy fab. <a href="https://www.globenewswire.com/news-release/2021/06/24/2252250/0/en/STMicroelectronics-brings-Tower-Semiconductor-on-board-300mm-analog-and-power-fab-under-construction-in-Italy.html">Tower Semi partnered with STMicroelectronics in 2021 to share the cleanroom of this fab</a>. Tower has 1/3rd of the cleanroom and helps ramp the cleanroom to higher utilization faster. </p><p>A simplified graphic of their fab footprint is below. </p><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F65f3112b-f836-433b-8a49-3dc7cb53a62d_1344x1396.png"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F65f3112b-f836-433b-8a49-3dc7cb53a62d_1344x1396.png" width="1344" height="1396" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/65f3112b-f836-433b-8a49-3dc7cb53a62d_1344x1396.png&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:1396,&quot;width&quot;:1344,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:1739047,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt=""></a></figure></div><p>Notice the types of deals Tower pursues, they are primarily JVs. Tower is the fab partner for many larger IDMs, and by acquiring Tower, Intel now has a new customer opportunity given the tight integration of JVs. Panasonic is Tower&#8217;s largest customer at ~25% of revenue, but there are 5 additional customers that account for 4-11% of sales. Then a long tail after that. The tail in particular is Intel&#8217;s opportunity. </p><p>I want to last talk about some of the niche products Tower has. They seem to be the leading Silicon Germanium (SiGe) manufacturer in the world, a specialty process that is useful for RF (radio frequency) front end. Tower is also a leader in silicon photonics fabrication.</p><p>In Tower&#8217;s own words their biggest drivers are RF CMOS, industrial sensors, RF mobile, and RF Infrastructure (datacom photonics). In particular, some amount of power ICs fabbing capability for Intel makes sense, RF CMOS likely is just nice to have, and RF infrastructure aligns almost directly with Intel&#8217;s future ambitions. </p><p>Notice the technology, the majority of their capacity is at the 200mm wafer sizing. While these fabs are &#8220;specialty&#8221; products, their 6-inch and 8-inch power capacity is not particularly special. I would say there is a good mix of leading specialties like the 300mm CMOS and SiGe (Silicon-Germanium), but the 150mm and 200mm power is relatively commoditized capacity. So now let&#8217;s discuss why Tower is a good fit for Intel. </p><h2>Intel Foundry Service&#8217;s Jump Start</h2><p>A reminder that Intel is not letting go of its Fab, but rather amplifying its fab capabilities in its &#8220;IDM 2.0&#8221; strategy. This is a renewed commitment to fabbing Intel&#8217;s own products, as well as opening up their fab and PDK (Process Design Kit) to other companies and customers. The thought here is that they can further leverage their large fab footprint and offer highly desired leading-edge foundry services to their customers in a time when companies desperately want more leading-edge capabilities. But where does Tower fit into that given their mostly lagging edge capacity? </p><p>I think Tower completes the fab footprint in a holistic sense. Imagine you want to fab something completely custom at Intel. It&#8217;s a whole unit of data center compute not just a CPU, with connected custom fabric, some silicon photonics, and of course, its power-hungry (PMICs). </p><p>In the current Intel world you could just get the leading edge chip and packaging, but not the rest of the silicon, photonics, or power IC that composes a total system. Imagine trying to buy a car and only being sold the engine and the ability to attach the engine to a car (packaging), that is the current scope of Intel Foundry Service (IFS). </p><p>Tower expands this. Now we have a full-service shop. And it&#8217;s no surprise actually if you look at their peer Taiwan Semiconductor, which is known for its leading-edge logic. But a closer look shows that 37% of TSMC&#8217;s revenue consists of geometries larger than 28nm. So in the case of TSMC, you can go to them and get the full solution. If IFS is to compete for head to head, they need Tower to complete their full solution.</p><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F6ee4e338-78a1-424f-9557-1e3b097a6d8d_1513x714.png"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F6ee4e338-78a1-424f-9557-1e3b097a6d8d_1513x714.png" width="1456" height="687" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/6ee4e338-78a1-424f-9557-1e3b097a6d8d_1513x714.png&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:687,&quot;width&quot;:1456,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:186736,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt=""></a></figure></div><p>This was discussed on their M&amp;A call: </p><blockquote><p>This combination of leading edge and specialty technologies will position us as a truly global end-to-end foundry. When we launched IFS last March, our customers were overwhelmingly excited to work with us. <strong>One of the things that consistently asked me was to add specialty and mature nodes to our portfolio. With Tower, we can honor that request and more broadly serve key market segments.</strong></p></blockquote><p>You can&#8217;t have a compelling IFS without making it full service. But more than that I think one of the biggest benefits is adding a new culture that is actually customer-centric. Some of the past critiques of Intel&#8217;s foundry plans were inflexibility and non-standard workflows. </p><p>Working with Intel in the past was like showing up at someone else&#8217;s garage and being forced to use their wacky tools and blueprints not being given much insight into how things were made. Tower has standard workflows and a more customer-centric fab culture, and this could be a huge kickstart to creating a standard workflow at IFS. </p><blockquote><p>Yes. And while some of this is premature to talk about it too much detail, given the regulatory process, my expectation is that we will fully merge IFS and Tower into a single foundry business for Intel going forward. And part of the value and the synergy of the acquisition as the question suggest, <strong>is to fully benefit from that decades of experience that Tower brings and how to run a global foundry customer-centric business for our customers for the future</strong>. So overall, we'll lay out more of that integration strategy as we get to the time of deal closure. <strong>But this will become one foundry business that will be the full integration of IFS today with Tower today.</strong></p></blockquote><p>So assuming IFS and Tower are all one unit, I am now warming up to a foundry spin. It was directly in opposition to what Pat Gelsinger has said before, but let&#8217;s examine it from the perspective of Gelsinger&#8217;s history and what he knows, aka the Dell corporate structure. </p><h2>Intel Might Spin Foundry Now</h2><p>I have followed the Dell complex (for lack of better words) at a surface level for a few years now. Michael Dell, the founder of the PC giant Dell, <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/antoinegara/2021/04/18/how-wall-streets-greatest-piece-of-financial-engineering-propelled-michael-dell-to-a-50-billion-fortune/?sh=75dbbb71482e">took Dell private in an audacious LBO with Silverlake</a>. Pat Gelsinger worked at one of the subsidiaries at the time, and the subsequent corporate structure is likely familiar to Pat. While I don&#8217;t think Pat Gelsinger is going to take the Dell route it&#8217;s good to look at the corporate patterns and behaviors he knows best. </p><p>For context, Pat Gelsinger joined EMC as COO in 2009 and has watched the entire Dell structure emerge. This included the EMC collapse into Dell and the spinout of VMWare back to public markets. I&#8217;m sure he&#8217;s well versed in the logic of spin-offs and tracking stocks that were used at Dell. In fact, you can argue that the <a href="https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/intels-mobileye-stub-and-positioning?r=qq5">partial spin of Mobileye looks a lot like something Dell did with Vmware originally</a>. I now think that this is what will happen in some capacity with Intel Foundry Services.</p><p>I don&#8217;t think this happens immediately because of the huge capital requirements of IFS, but I do think that post Mobileye spin, the promise of an IFS will be a carrot held over investors&#8217; heads. IFS will be a completely separate unit, and now it has a history of financials and some kind of internal structure that it will inherit from Tower. It&#8217;s primed to spin. </p><p>I think that it will be mentioned as a &#8220;strategic option given market conditions&#8221; and broken out segment-wise. This will force investors to start to consider Intel as a SOTP valuation first and foremost. I know that this seems like a headache but Pat&#8217;s primary focus is likely on the technology side of things, and it&#8217;s easy to slip into what he knows corporate structure-wise. Especially when it enriched the Dell CEO so much. And having that potential option is going to be a valuable card to play in my opinion.</p><p>Intel would become a quasi holding company in this scenario, with partial stakes in faster-growing businesses (MBLY, IFS) while its core fabless business itself would be likely a slower growth entity that gets to benefit from its partial stakes in these tracking stocks. This sounds frankly the future of Intel. Now let&#8217;s move on to what to expect from Investor day. </p><h2>Intel&#8217;s Investor Day</h2><p>I am for one excited for Investor day. Here are a few of the things I expect.</p><ul><li><p>Resegments and new long term models for each segment</p></li><li><p><strong>An absolute kitchen sinking of FY22 numbers</strong> </p><ul><li><p>Guide up revenue marginally</p></li><li><p>Gross margins sub 52%</p></li><li><p>Guide down earnings </p></li></ul></li><li><p>Some kind of FCF guide </p></li><li><p>An aggressive Capex plan, possibly matching TSMC</p></li><li><p>Mobileye discussion, and the hint of spinning IFS eventually</p></li><li><p>Progress reports on their catch up plan </p><ul><li><p>They will promise performance parity in 2023</p></li></ul></li></ul><p>I&#8217;m almost certain I will be surprised by something they have. I expect some kind of product announcement, and in particular, I would love to hear more about their DPU. Dylan at Semiananalysis has been all over their DPU. </p><p>I wanted to make a bingo sheet but didn&#8217;t have exactly enough time. I&#8217;ll be watching and live-tweeting the whole event on <a href="https://twitter.com/_fabknowledge_">@_fabknowledge_ </a></p><p>I will of course be drinking every time Pat says something horny, e.g. &#8220;puberty&#8221; at Intel, or &#8220;lusts&#8221; for fabs. <strong>But I&#8217;m excited about a good show and have to say, I am the most bullish I have been on Intel in a while. I think there is a chance they can really surprise us</strong>, and while I know that the FY22 numbers are about to get brought down, I believe that most investors already know this. Everyone knows that, and in recent days every expected miss has been reversed. I expect that to happen at Intel. </p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Earnings Roundup: 2/11/2022]]></title><description><![CDATA[ON, ACLS, RMBS, AOSL, CAMT, ICHR, ONTO, SUMCO, and more!]]></description><link>https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/earnings-roundup-2112022</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/earnings-roundup-2112022</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Doug (mule)]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 11 Feb 2022 17:00:13 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/h_600,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F6652f918-2de1-4f17-a292-8807d8d6cafa_1346x988.png" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2>SUMCO</h2><p>SUMCO was the best call I read this quarter. There were many great bits of information but I want to start with the stat that really shocked me. </p><blockquote><p>First of all, with regard to the LTAs out to 2026 and whether we did make progress in the last 3 months, that is correct. In the last 3 months, we were ultimately able to fully lock in LTAs for all of the capacity.</p></blockquote><p>Additionally, both SUMCO and Global Wafers were extremely adamant that supply couldn&#8217;t be brought on immediately as they are missing key tools to add capacity and they believe that output won&#8217;t start ramping until 2023. They will continue to ramp their new factory until 2025, but that won&#8217;t be enough to satisfy wafer demand. </p><p>Until then the thing that will continue for wafer companies is price raises. These price rises are yet another part of <a href="https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/the-rising-tide-of-semiconductor">why semiconductor costs are rising everywhere</a>. SUMCO&#8217;s price raises are 10% annually until 2024, mostly to offset the increasing rise of deprecation for their capacity ramp. </p><p>The thing that was so confusing is if they are raising prices 10% a year, adding capacity, and most of their operating profit growth was primarily from price raises, why aren&#8217;t they pushing more capacity ASAP? Part of it seems to be an oligopoly decision from Shin-Etsu, Global Wafers, and SUMCO, but another part is it truly seems like they cannot. They are having the same lead time problem as the rest of the fabs.</p><blockquote><p>Sadly, there are many individual processes to fabricating a wafer at SUMCO. So regardless of the price of the equipment, the absence of even a single piece of equipment will prevent us from completing the wafer fabrication process.</p></blockquote><p>The next part that gave me pause was they believe that their demand model is booked out to 2026, inclusive of industry capacity additions. <strong>Given there really are only 3 wafer suppliers, I candidly have to ask what the hell is going on? Will we be talking about wafer shortages 2 years from now?</strong> </p><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F6652f918-2de1-4f17-a292-8807d8d6cafa_1346x988.png"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F6652f918-2de1-4f17-a292-8807d8d6cafa_1346x988.png" width="1346" height="988" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/6652f918-2de1-4f17-a292-8807d8d6cafa_1346x988.png&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:988,&quot;width&quot;:1346,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:278866,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt=""></a></figure></div><p>Part of the problem is that ramping greenfield investment is something that SUMCO said was extremely challenging for them in 2017, and this will be challenging to ramp greenfield again. </p><blockquote><p>Unfortunately, the lack of experience meant that we really struggled in 2017 and 2018. We have since focused on learning from our mistakes, and mistakes often create the biggest opportunity for learnings. As a result, this time around, our workforce is much more experienced and prepared.</p><p>And as an organization, because of our previous struggles, we now have a deeper bench of experienced workers. This is why we believe we can undertake this kind of large-scale expansion. That is my view.</p><p>I would also say that equipment operators require significant accumulated experience. These are not the kind of jobs, where you can pick up the skills very easily over a short period of time.</p></blockquote><p>Another part of the wafer shortage story that made me ask &#8220;WTF&#8221; out loud once again was the 200mm wafers. SUMCO said that they would never add 200mm wafers and that there is no way to increase 200mm wafers. All of their supply improvements have been brownfield expansion and according to SUMCO, the 2021 capacity additions are the end of their brownfield ability to expand. The equipment no longer exists. </p><blockquote><p>It is possible that 200-millimeter prices could continue to rise over time. Equally, you could see a pause in the rise in prices. There is no way to increase 200-millimeter volume. T<strong>he equipment is no longer available and older facilities that have been idled, are obsolete. So increasing volume is not possible.</strong></p></blockquote><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fc4f2a279-10fb-41f8-af2e-1085675d39b3_1346x906.png"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fc4f2a279-10fb-41f8-af2e-1085675d39b3_1346x906.png" width="1346" height="906" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/c4f2a279-10fb-41f8-af2e-1085675d39b3_1346x906.png&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:906,&quot;width&quot;:1346,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:402927,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt=""></a><figcaption class="image-caption">As good as it&#8217;s going to get</figcaption></figure></div><p>The trailing edge looks like it will be the worst impacted by price raises, especially 150mm and 200mm wafers. Price raises will likely continue as long as there are mission-critical and qualified products that are unlikely to swap over. Think of automotive analog and other products. Meanwhile, 200mm wafers will never see additions of capacity. <a href="https://www.zdnet.com/article/this-old-programming-language-is-suddenly-hot-again-but-its-future-is-still-far-from-certain/">This is a bit reminiscent of the Fortran programming shortage</a>. </p><p>Anyways I want to talk about the other slides they had in their deck, particularly their demand graphs and their customer inventory graphs. </p><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fe6858527-bd7e-4ec6-8431-7444aa6d2fb7_1394x927.png"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fe6858527-bd7e-4ec6-8431-7444aa6d2fb7_1394x927.png" width="1394" height="927" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/e6858527-bd7e-4ec6-8431-7444aa6d2fb7_1394x927.png&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:927,&quot;width&quot;:1394,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:123735,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt=""></a></figure></div><p>First, let&#8217;s talk about their demand builds. They expect Smartphone units to increase at a 4.9% CAGR from 1.3 billion units to 1.65 billion units, but starting points matter. From 2019 at 1.48 billion units this is only a 1.9% unit CAGR. So the real differential is content increases, they expect approximately 4.5% annual content increases in smartphones. That sounds correct to me. </p><p>Next, they talk about HPC demand, and I really liked this unit analysis because I have never seen anyone take a crack at it before. </p><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F653a2e10-6bd1-460d-9d7f-b99884986c2d_1363x921.png"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F653a2e10-6bd1-460d-9d7f-b99884986c2d_1363x921.png" width="1363" height="921" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/653a2e10-6bd1-460d-9d7f-b99884986c2d_1363x921.png&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:921,&quot;width&quot;:1363,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:112785,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt=""></a></figure></div><p>They believe that HPC will be approximately a ~14.7% CAGR in unit growth, and given its the largest incremental growth market I believe that this is correct. I believe that value will likely outgrow this, but something like a mid-double-digit value CAGR plus ~15% unit CAGR will net us to a 20%+ growth market. </p><p>On to DRAM and NAND. They expect DRAM bit growth rate to be approximately 20% and scaling to be 10%, so wafer volume growth will be the differential at 10%. </p><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F53c0aec3-5d9f-480e-88ed-654768274342_1340x944.png"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F53c0aec3-5d9f-480e-88ed-654768274342_1340x944.png" width="1340" height="944" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/53c0aec3-5d9f-480e-88ed-654768274342_1340x944.png&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:944,&quot;width&quot;:1340,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:167398,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt=""></a></figure></div><p>NAND&#8217;s bit growth has essentially kept in line with the demand rate, with a slight differential that shows up in wafer demand (1%). But going forward bit growth will start to decelerate and one of the ways to solve this is to bond wafers together, and this will be a new incremental wafer demand.</p><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F9cdb9c80-09f6-410e-9c3e-d73e322a6724_1304x958.png"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F9cdb9c80-09f6-410e-9c3e-d73e322a6724_1304x958.png" width="1304" height="958" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/9cdb9c80-09f6-410e-9c3e-d73e322a6724_1304x958.png&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:958,&quot;width&quot;:1304,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:185433,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt=""></a></figure></div><p>Last but not least I want to talk about their inventory graphs. I really don&#8217;t know how to read the graphs, and I interrupted this as colored as their estimates and the trailing as historical quarterly inventory builds. Are the forward estimates monthly or quarterly? The number scheming implies monthly. </p><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F796bd610-3250-4abc-9c3c-44a5bf712d42_1315x961.png"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F796bd610-3250-4abc-9c3c-44a5bf712d42_1315x961.png" width="1315" height="961" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/796bd610-3250-4abc-9c3c-44a5bf712d42_1315x961.png&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:961,&quot;width&quot;:1315,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:535592,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt=""></a></figure></div><p>They believe that wafer inventories are falling massively right now, as depletion is starting to take customers below 1 month of inventory. </p><blockquote><p>This chart shows estimated customer inventory for 300-millimeter wafers. You can clearly see the sharp decline in customer inventories. This is for 300-millimeter wafers as a whole. We believe that customer inventory has dropped to 1 month. If inventories drop below the 1-month level, it creates a precarious situation for the customers.</p><p>&nbsp;If we then look at the next slide, Slide 11, which breaks out customer 300-millimeter wafer inventory between logic and memory, you can see that logic is already at 0.7 months, while memory is around 1.2 months. So as you can see, the shortages are particularly acute for logic.</p></blockquote><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5d2b1630-fac5-44ca-978d-ab76719c3b24_1280x910.png"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5d2b1630-fac5-44ca-978d-ab76719c3b24_1280x910.png" width="1280" height="910" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/5d2b1630-fac5-44ca-978d-ab76719c3b24_1280x910.png&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:910,&quot;width&quot;:1280,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:463500,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt=""></a></figure></div><p>I am unsure what to make of this, but they essentially believe that memory customer inventory spiked during the 2019 cycle, remained high until 2021, but now are going to systematically decrease. I thought the inventory charts in general brought more questions up than answered. Inventories are clearly down at Logic (makes sense) but up in memory and rising (that is bearish!) but should come down soon (good!).  </p><p>Maybe the context of their entire capacity being booked until 2026 paired with falling inventories is the point they were trying to make. There is information for both the bears and bulls in this chart.</p><p>The rest of the earning update is behind a paywall, I just thought everyone should read the SUMCO update. </p>
      <p>
          <a href="https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/earnings-roundup-2112022">
              Read more
          </a>
      </p>
   ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[A Pure Play on Datacenter Memory and CXL]]></title><description><![CDATA[A spring load signals the long term potential of an underfollowed semiconductor company]]></description><link>https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/a-pure-play-on-datacenter-memory</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/a-pure-play-on-datacenter-memory</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Doug (mule)]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 08 Feb 2022 21:00:33 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/h_600,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F09b06190-9efb-49d4-a8c6-409ccf9c6a08_993x431.png" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[
      <p>
          <a href="https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/a-pure-play-on-datacenter-memory">
              Read more
          </a>
      </p>
   ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Earnings Roundup Week of 2/4/2022: Part 2]]></title><description><![CDATA[AMZN, FORM, F, SITM, MXL, IFX, MCHP, NOD, SYNA, TXN. This one is a long one.]]></description><link>https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/earnings-roundup-week-of-242022-part</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/earnings-roundup-week-of-242022-part</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Doug (mule)]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 06 Feb 2022 20:37:15 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/h_600,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F2fcf96b9-d4f7-4771-80c2-643738e743d0_1491x770.png" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>First I would be remiss to not briefly mention Facebook. Facebook&#8217;s huge IDFA related miss has absolutely punished the entire market. I want to reiterate that their capex spending plan is still in-line, so that&#8217;s good for Semis but bad for Facebook&#8217;s margins.</p><h2>Amazon Capex Conversation</h2><p>This is the first time they have ever broken out the magnitude of AWS&#8217;s spending I believe. </p><blockquote><p>Let's talk a little bit about capital expenditures. And I'm going to do this with the inclusion of equipment finance leases. So when you look at those numbers and how they've grown over the last few years, its about 40% -- <strong>just under 40% of that CapEx is going into infrastructure, most of it's feeding AWS.</strong></p><p>If I look to the future, we're still working through some of our plans 2022, but it's coming into focus a bit. <strong>We see the CapEx for infrastructure going up.</strong> We still have a very fast-growing business this growing globally, and we're adding regions and capacity to handle usage that still exceeds revenue growth in that business. So we feel good about making those investments</p></blockquote><p>No context of magnitude, but all of the hyperscalers point to &#8220;increasing&#8221; capex in 2022. </p><h2>Texas Instruments Capital Management Day</h2><p>I&#8217;m kind of shocked that Texas Instruments&#8217; capital plan was taken &#8220;poorly&#8221;. They are pretty explicit about the why for their new aggressive capex growth plan, and while FCF margins might be taken down, <strong>FCF per share growth is going to be supported by higher growth. </strong></p><p>Here&#8217;s their slide:</p><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F2fcf96b9-d4f7-4771-80c2-643738e743d0_1491x770.png"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F2fcf96b9-d4f7-4771-80c2-643738e743d0_1491x770.png" width="1456" height="752" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/2fcf96b9-d4f7-4771-80c2-643738e743d0_1491x770.png&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:752,&quot;width&quot;:1456,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:164250,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt=""></a></figure></div><p>And a meaningful part of the investment is in 300-millimeter, an area where they have a 40% less expensive chip! Even if it&#8217;s more expensive the blended cost of goods sold is much better. All of their investment will be at 300 millimeters of course.</p><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F94fb0e28-13c6-4122-a113-b2992a294671_1453x698.png"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F94fb0e28-13c6-4122-a113-b2992a294671_1453x698.png" width="1453" height="698" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/94fb0e28-13c6-4122-a113-b2992a294671_1453x698.png&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:698,&quot;width&quot;:1453,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:98774,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt=""></a></figure></div><p>Their long-term growth guidance is actually in excess of their historical 10-year revenue growth, further supporting the secular case. Yes FCF margins might suffer in the terminal years, but they just told you that they more than expect to make up for it with growth driven by content increases. <strong>They also aren&#8217;t even accounting for the CHIPS act for any of these investments, which they will be a large beneficiary from.</strong> </p><p>The company is making a big but not that bold bet on their future, and they are saying the terminal value of the company is going to be growing at a much faster rate. Investors of course are concerned about what that means for the next 4 years of FCF, as they will be spending more. I think it&#8217;s a moot point, they will earn a great cost on the capital deployed and they believe they have an opportunity to deploy more capital, especially post CHIPS act. And now the stock is 10% cheaper for it.</p><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F712e3fb2-477b-4fea-bfbf-90754028c6ba_2400x1240.png"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F712e3fb2-477b-4fea-bfbf-90754028c6ba_2400x1240.png" width="1456" height="752" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/712e3fb2-477b-4fea-bfbf-90754028c6ba_2400x1240.png&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:752,&quot;width&quot;:1456,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt=""></a></figure></div><p>I hate to use the word &#8220;long term&#8221; so repetitively, but if you&#8217;re in it for the long term the company is guiding you to a better future with higher revenue growth but the market will of course punish their FCF degradation in the short term. There&#8217;s nothing wrong here, and I think investors should relish this opportunity. A little bit of volatility in a bad tape makes this an opportunity. </p><div><hr></div><h2>Infineon</h2><p>Infineon was odd. They had a beat and raise which most automotive companies did, but by far the oddest part is their capex plans. Let&#8217;s first talk about their FY outlook - 17.5% revenue growth. </p><blockquote><p>For the entire fiscal 2022, we are increasing our revenue guidance, taking account the stronger dollar from EUR 12.7 billion to EUR 13 billion, plus or minus EUR 500 million. In the middle of the range, this would mean growth of 17.5% compared to the previous year.</p></blockquote><p>When you consider their growth and their guidance to $1 billion in FCF, this is where I go &#8220;hmm&#8221;.  Last year they did ~$1.8 billion in FCF, and they didn&#8217;t nuke their margin estimates either, yet are guiding down FCF. They guided up their Capex growth by 35%, but their FCF down by ~80%. They talk about how some of this will go to supply agreements, but I don&#8217;t completely buy it. </p><blockquote><p>I'd be glad to answer your question. From a purely arithmetic point of view, you're absolutely right. If you push up revenue to EUR 2 billion and push up earnings, it should have a slight improving effect on free cash flow.</p><p>There are 2 reasons why we didn't do this. We have an around in front of the figures and I think that, that would cover slightly higher values as well. Secondly, in terms of substance, in order to secure the supply side, especially with external partners, here and there, we are in talks where we are asked to make advanced payments to participate in investments.</p><p>Since this risk exists, since we are exposed to this risk and accepted in order to secure future growth, this would weigh on free cash flow. This is why we have introduced a small risk position.</p></blockquote><p>I think analysts were also surprised, and their first question on the call is why not spend more? They said well they are limited by their ability to acquire tools, and they even broke out their expected value of the $2.4 billion is $1.5 billion shells. Yet no meaningful capex for tools. </p><p>The key part in my opinion is they explicitly say that their investment plans are not including the CHIPS act or any kind of subsidies. If you&#8217;re reading between the lines they expect to spend more post-EU CHIPS act. I found this move extremely odd given everyone else is investing heavily and now Infineon is not.</p><p>Before we move on, I want to just highlight some comments they have on Automotive. They note that they think that SAAR will return to similar to pre-2019 levels, and even if a supply-demand shortage was resolved production still needs to increase. </p><blockquote><p>Global car production in 2021 was 76.4 million units, which is only slightly higher than the level of 2020. The analysts at IHS Markit thinks that because of bottlenecks with semiconductors and other components and different problems in the supply chain, about 10 million cars were not built.</p><p>The following interaction is also important here. The shortage of semiconductors means that the car manufacturers prefer to use the chips available to them in higher-value cars. As a rule, they need more semiconductors than vehicles in the compact class, such as advanced driver assistance systems. This prioritization will have a further effect of holding back the total number of new vehicles.</p><p>For 2022, a gradual reduction in the bottlenecks is expected, which IHS has forecast for this year, namely 82.9 million vehicles, but that would still be well below the production level for 2018 and 2019. <strong>The supply bottlenecks are, therefore, far from over and will continue well into 2022.</strong></p></blockquote><div><hr></div><h2>Ford on Semiconductors</h2><p>The best semiconductor transcript surprisingly goes to&#8230;. Ford! The entire blurb is worth reading. </p><blockquote><p><strong>Perhaps the biggest gift for all the pain we're going through now in semiconductors is that we have very painfully learned the lesson that we cannot manage the supply chain for these key components as we have</strong>. In fact, you could argue that in the change of transition to these digital electric vehicles that supply chain could be one of the biggest advantages a particular company has or doesn't have.</p><p>The way we look at it is the key electric components, memory chips, semiconductors. I would break semiconductors into 2 types. Feature-rich chips that we still use a lot. A window regulator doesn't need to have a 4-nanometer chip. And the advanced -- but we also have sensors, power electronics for our inverters, the batteries themselves all the way back to the mine, the inverters of different battery. Chemistries itself have different raw materials and kind of ecosystems that support them. So this is a very important topic for the company.</p><p>How different it is? It's really different. We need different talent at the company. We need physical inspection of the actual producers. We need direct contracts with them. We need to design the SoC ourselves. We need to direct in the case -- in some cases, to even direct prefer build to print or actually use supplier XYZ to get out of where we've been. And this takes talent. It takes a different approach. It takes more resources.</p><p>On GlobalFoundries, it's kind of the first big bet, but there'll be many, many more coming for us. We're very dependent on TSMC for our feature-rich nodes. Obviously, the capacity is at risk over time as the industry moves to more advanced nodes, including us. And as I said, we're going to need feature-rich nodes for many years to come. GlobalFoundries knows how to build them. They know to build them in the United States. We can partner with the government, depending on the CHIPS Act to capacitize here. It will be a few years until we benefit from that, but it's a really big thing to descale ourselves on the feature-rich chips from the current ecosystem that we depend on around the world. And I think GlobalFoundries is a really interesting deal when we get into the details.</p><p>We have to put cash up when we participate. Those feature-rich semis will be used by other companies, industrial companies, not just Ford. It's a really interesting deal. And I was talking to the U.S. government today about how critical this is for our company. You can expect the same kind of thing on advanced nodes and all the other components I mentioned, including more deals on the raw material for various types of battery chemistry. And this is a culture change at Ford. As I said, this is part of the rhythm change between ICE and BEV.</p></blockquote><p>Ford pretty much said they are culturally becoming a semiconductor-focused company. Love it. </p><div><hr></div>
      <p>
          <a href="https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/earnings-roundup-week-of-242022-part">
              Read more
          </a>
      </p>
   ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Earnings Roundup for the Week of 1/31 - Part 1 ]]></title><description><![CDATA[Another week of earnings: NXPI, CRUS, ENTG, AMD, MELE, SLAB. Plus an Idea!]]></description><link>https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/earnings-roundup-for-the-week-of</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/earnings-roundup-for-the-week-of</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Doug (mule)]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 02 Feb 2022 21:00:31 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/h_600,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fa4ac9181-3e3d-4133-86af-5d423a5486e9_2400x1240.png" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[
      <p>
          <a href="https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/earnings-roundup-for-the-week-of">
              Read more
          </a>
      </p>
   ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Earnings: Texas Instruments, KLA, Lam Research and More]]></title><description><![CDATA[An action packed week for Semiconductor Earnings]]></description><link>https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/earnings-texas-instruments-kla-lam</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/earnings-texas-instruments-kla-lam</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Doug (mule)]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 29 Jan 2022 20:00:29 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/h_600,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbcfa8271-a7ef-49da-898a-67b2d85334bf_361x419.png" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[
      <p>
          <a href="https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/earnings-texas-instruments-kla-lam">
              Read more
          </a>
      </p>
   ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Semiconductors and Markets]]></title><description><![CDATA[Semiconductors are high-beta. They are considered economically sensitive. Does that Matter Right Now?]]></description><link>https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/semiconductors-and-markets</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/semiconductors-and-markets</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Doug (mule)]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 24 Jan 2022 23:57:37 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/h_600,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F8893fc2c-d070-4bb4-a250-9318458a60eb_2400x1240.png" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[
      <p>
          <a href="https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/semiconductors-and-markets">
              Read more
          </a>
      </p>
   ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[How France's Largest Semiconductor Company Got Nationalized in Plain Sight]]></title><description><![CDATA[A power struggle was actually China encroaching on France's Largest Company. France decided to nationalize instead.]]></description><link>https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/how-frances-largest-semiconductor</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/how-frances-largest-semiconductor</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Doug (mule)]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 21 Jan 2022 18:52:46 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/6f20f443-b1bc-4075-94db-feaf5695c59b_1719x1148.png" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong>TLDR: China owned a 10.93% stake in Soitec and could have pushed to control it, but instead France just nationalized the company. In a series of power plays, the French board installed a CEO who best reflected National Interests. Management got blindsided. </strong></p><div><hr></div><p>Soitec is a semiconductor materials company known for its smart cut and Silicon on Insulator (SOI) technologies, which are critical in 5G, Silicon Photonics, and Silicon Carbide (EV) end-markets. </p><p>Yesterday, they announced that current CEO Paul Boudre will retire and be replaced by Pierre Barnab&#233; in July of 2022. Barnab&#233; is currently an SVP at Atos, a French IT consulting company. This seemingly routine CEO transition sank company shares by over 15%. It&#8217;s not what it seems. </p><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F460c4cb8-1327-496b-b8f6-3c651dcb8fc8_718x482.png"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F460c4cb8-1327-496b-b8f6-3c651dcb8fc8_718x482.png" width="718" height="482" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/460c4cb8-1327-496b-b8f6-3c651dcb8fc8_718x482.png&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:482,&quot;width&quot;:718,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:55227,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt=""></a></figure></div><p>First, <strong>the entire existing management team is opposed</strong>. <a href="https://news.in-24.com/business/509334.html">The management team </a>sent a <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2022-01-20/soitec-sinks-after-board-surprises-investors-with-new-ceo-pick">letter to the board</a> that does not mince words. Translated to English, it reads:</p><blockquote><p>Soitec's Management Committee deplores the takeover of Soitec by the Chairman of the Board of Directors for 3 years, which culminates today with the incomprehensible appointment of a new CEO.</p></blockquote><p>What exactly is happening at Soitec? Well first let&#8217;s just start with the current story of the now outgoing CEO, Paul Boudre. </p><h2>The Story of Soitec (and Paul Boudre)</h2><p>Soitec, like most firms, was no overnight success. This <a href="https://www.soitec.com/en/company/soitec-activity/history">timeline of the companies history</a> is the best place to start. Soitec originally pursued other markets but failed to gain traction. In 2015, the company <a href="https://www.renewableenergyworld.com/solar/soitec-to-shutter-germany-cpv-manufacturing-regroup-its-san-diego-facility/">Soitec shuttered its solar business</a> as part of a hard pivot away from its existing failures. </p><p>The situation was dire. The company had more debt than the value of its market capitalization.</p><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5c608507-44e4-4748-8346-425e022342ad_2400x1240.png"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5c608507-44e4-4748-8346-425e022342ad_2400x1240.png" width="1100" height="568" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/5c608507-44e4-4748-8346-425e022342ad_2400x1240.png&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:568,&quot;width&quot;:1100,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt=""></a><figcaption class="image-caption">For context Soitec today is a ~5.8 billion euro company now</figcaption></figure></div><p>In January of 2015, with shares trading at measly $200 million market capitalization, Paul Boudre was appointed CEO. Paul initially joined the company from KLA as an Executive VP in Sales before transitioning to COO in 2008. Drastic changes were needed.</p><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff70e3a1f-75f4-42bb-a40a-2e8613eeb1cc_1493x915.png"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff70e3a1f-75f4-42bb-a40a-2e8613eeb1cc_1493x915.png" width="596" height="365.18545454545455" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/f70e3a1f-75f4-42bb-a40a-2e8613eeb1cc_1493x915.png&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:674,&quot;width&quot;:1100,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:596,&quot;bytes&quot;:190549,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt=""></a><figcaption class="image-caption">Soitec&#8217;s rather bleak 2015</figcaption></figure></div><p>In the midst of significant layoffs in the solar division, a hefty financing package company to keep the company afloat, Paul focused the company on SOI and made it what it is today. </p><p>The details of the turnaround are unimportant, but the results today speak for themselves: Soitec now boasts a ~$5.8B market capitalization (~29x higher than the start of his tenure) and has 4x+ annual revenue. This is a legendary turnaround that will surely be sung of in Semiconductor Valhalla. </p><p>At the age of 63, Paul is approaching retirement. Given such a track record, one imagines a thoughtful process involving existing management, not the overnight skullduggery that actually occurred. Further, the new CEO candidate has no experience in the semiconductor field. <strong>Why did the board choose newcomer Pierre Barnab&#233; over other qualified internal candidates?</strong> </p><p>To answer this, we need to learn about the Chairman of the Board.  </p><h2>Enter Eric Meurice (and Pierre)</h2><p>Eric Meurice is best known as the former CEO of ASML. In 2013 Eric was appointed Chairman of the board of ASML after 8 years of being CEO. Note the exact lanaguage of the Chairman announcement.  </p><blockquote><p>Eric Meurice will be Chairman of ASML Holding and act as adviser to the new leadership and the Supervisory Board <strong>until the end of his contract on 31&nbsp;March 2014</strong>, ensuring a smooth and comprehensive transition of critical tasks and processes, customer contacts and relations with strategic suppliers. </p></blockquote><p>The current CEO gets the job during Eric Meurice&#8217;s contract and Mr. Meurice gets bumped to Chairman. It&#8217;s pretty customary for the outgoing CEO to spend time as the current Chairman. It&#8217;s less customary to not have the contract renewed. Despite <a href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/SB116034709363786253">European CEOs having shorter tenures</a>, this is atypical. </p><p>As the former CEO of ASML, Eric Meurice is now an ideal candidate for board memberships. Here&#8217;s a list of the few boards he&#8217;s been a part of. </p><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://www.bloomberg.com/profile/person/6442472"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb43b2d12-d7e0-4840-971f-b771426c53be_1011x543.png" width="1011" height="543" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/b43b2d12-d7e0-4840-971f-b771426c53be_1011x543.png&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:543,&quot;width&quot;:1011,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:45029,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:&quot;https://www.bloomberg.com/profile/person/6442472&quot;}" class="sizing-normal" alt=""></a><figcaption class="image-caption"><a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/profile/person/6442472">From Bloomberg Profiles</a></figcaption></figure></div><p>Let&#8217;s hone in on Eric&#8217;s stint at Soitec. Eric Meurice joined the board of Soitec in 2018 as the chair of the Nomination Committee. The committee was tasked with nominating a new Chairman, so else does Eric Meurice nominate but himself? </p><p>Eric, overqualified as he is, gets the job. But that&#8217;s not enough. In 2019, he picks up two more important roles as the Chair of the Strategic Committee and <strong>Chair of the Compensation Committee. He now holds both the keys to the kingdom and to its treasury. </strong></p><p>Joining a company, becoming the Chairman of the Board, and then taking on additional roles as the head of the Compensation and Strategic Committees fit into the typical model of a high-powered executive. That&#8217;s standard.</p><p>How does the French Government fit into Eric&#8217;s rise to power? </p><h3>Eric Meurice&#8217;s Extraordinary Actions</h3><p>Let&#8217;s look at the specific actions Eric Meurice took that prompted significant backlash from the executive committee. In the executive committee letter, they listed out a few specific complaints that were (importantly) falsifiable. Their (translated) list of grievances is as follows: </p><ul><li><p><strong>Takeover of the interim compensation committee that has become definitive, creating an omnipresence in all committees and at the head of several committees</strong></p></li><li><p>Interference in social dialogue without consultation with management.</p></li><li><p>Double language regarding the opposition of management on the implementation of PAT (Action Plan for All) in 2021.</p></li><li><p><strong>Establishment of internal regulations granting exceptionally extensive powers to the Chairman of the Board of Directors and establishing the keys to his takeover.</strong></p></li><li><p>Alteration of evidence in the context of the investigation of a governance drift.</p></li><li><p>Intimidation, vexatious practices towards members of the Executive Committee.</p></li></ul><p>The board granted itself extensive power through a list of resolutions added to the typical bylaws of the company at the so-called &#8220;extraordinary shareholders general meeting&#8221;. It&#8217;s rare to see an extraordinary resolution, <strong>so it&#8217;s outright mind-boggling to see 35 resolutions</strong>. This is one of the broadest power grabs I&#8217;ve ever seen. Let&#8217;s consider a few of the resolutions.</p><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fa59c08f8-53be-4c27-b9ef-392ec6e1350f_907x439.png"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fa59c08f8-53be-4c27-b9ef-392ec6e1350f_907x439.png" width="907" height="439" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/a59c08f8-53be-4c27-b9ef-392ec6e1350f_907x439.png&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:439,&quot;width&quot;:907,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:124738,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt=""></a><figcaption class="image-caption">There are a total of 35 resolutions, each giving the board more power than a typical board would have. </figcaption></figure></div><p>The resolutions are technical, but the gist of them is that the board now has a whole set of new powers that are usually reserved for the CFO. They can issue shares, buy back shares, decide who gets shares, and <strong>all of these powers are directly granted to the board.</strong> This creates extraordinary power to the board and the people on it.   </p><p>This explains why they had 3 CFOs since the extraordinary resolutions began. Remy Pierre was replaced in <a href="https://www.globenewswire.com/news-release/2019/09/05/1911267/0/fr/SOITEC-ANNONCE-LA-NOMINATION-DE-S%C3%89BASTIEN-ROUGE-COMME-DIRECTEUR-FINANCIER.html">September 2019 by S&#233;bastien Rouge</a> who was replaced one year later by <a href="https://www.globenewswire.com/news-release/2020/07/03/2057265/0/en/SOITEC-ANNOUNCES-THE-DEPARTURE-OF-SEBASTIEN-ROUGE-CFO-TO-BE-REPLACED-BY-LEA-ALZINGRE-APPOINTED-ACTING-CFO.html">Lea Alzingre</a>. That&#8217;s high turnover for the job.</p><p>Maybe these resolutions could be kosher, but the reason they are not is all the extraordinary resolutions are new for Soitec. Take 2017 for example, when there were only 6 plain resolutions. Something has changed. </p><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5c06e30c-0a8e-4f59-8424-ef0b30597226_1212x846.png"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5c06e30c-0a8e-4f59-8424-ef0b30597226_1212x846.png" width="516" height="360.26181818181817" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/5c06e30c-0a8e-4f59-8424-ef0b30597226_1212x846.png&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:768,&quot;width&quot;:1100,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:516,&quot;bytes&quot;:203278,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt=""></a><figcaption class="image-caption">6 routine resolutions in 2017.</figcaption></figure></div><p>But besides the mundane extraordinary powers of resolutions given to the board, there&#8217;s more at play. I now want to focus on the executive committee complaint around the compensation board because this is where the other players (France) start to enter the scene. </p><h2>Board Power Politics</h2><p>Let&#8217;s talk about the composition of the board. The board power politics make sense when you can see who is sits on what board committees. There are 5 board committees in Soitec, and the restricted strategic meeting is an ad-hoc group for acquisitions or other events. So that means there are really 4 standing committees and 1 ad-hoc committee. They are the Strategic Committee, the Audit Committee, the Nomination Committee, and the Compensation Committee.  </p><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd308e96c-4191-4294-a938-488da3ba863c_1020x1128.png"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd308e96c-4191-4294-a938-488da3ba863c_1020x1128.png" width="1020" height="1128" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/d308e96c-4191-4294-a938-488da3ba863c_1020x1128.png&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:1128,&quot;width&quot;:1020,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:328206,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt=""></a></figure></div><p>These committees are filled with 14 members, many of them are supposed to be independent. This breaks down with further examination as many of the &#8220;independents&#8221; are clearly affiliated with the French Government. Now let&#8217;s start with chairs of the five committees. </p><p><strong>Eric Meurice</strong> is the <strong>Chairman of the Board</strong>, <strong>Chair of the Compensation Committee</strong> (most powerful committee), and <strong>the Chair of the Strategic Committee</strong>. </p><p><strong>Laurence Delpy</strong> is <strong>Chair of the Nomination Committee</strong>, the chair that Eric Meurice previously held before he became Chairman of the Board. She&#8217;s independent, yet she sits on all 5 committees. </p><p><strong>Lastly, Christophe Gegout</strong> is chair of the Audit and Risk Committees. He&#8217;s supposed to be an independent member, <strong>but he used to work for CEA aka the large French consortium with a meaningful stake in Soitec</strong>. He doesn&#8217;t work there anymore, but they&#8217;re clearly playing fast and loose with the definition of the word &#8220;independent&#8221;.</p><p>Let&#8217;s look at the actual composition of the committees and identify 1) who is in what committee and 2) which committees matter. I made a simple graphic based on the filing with a legend that explains where everyone&#8217;s allegiances lie. In order of importance, it&#8217;s the Compensation, the Nomination, the Strategic &amp; Restricted Strategic, and lastly the Audit committee. I broadly categorized the board members into the 4 &#8220;teams&#8221;, aka Team France, Team China, Independent, and Employee Directors. Note the legend in the picture below.</p><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F644ddd59-6f6d-4c10-ab27-80a6f6e7f5b5_1650x1044.png"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F644ddd59-6f6d-4c10-ab27-80a6f6e7f5b5_1650x1044.png" width="1100" height="696" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/644ddd59-6f6d-4c10-ab27-80a6f6e7f5b5_1650x1044.png&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:696,&quot;width&quot;:1100,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:483412,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt=""></a><figcaption class="image-caption">Notice the legend in the photo above. Team Blue / France is the one to watch</figcaption></figure></div><p>Let&#8217;s start backward. The green team is employee directors and is part of a movement to get labor union leaders on the board so employees have more say in the company writ large. For the sake of this analysis, I consider them non-players, as this is their first year on the board, and they don&#8217;t sit on committees. </p><p>Next is the team &#8220;actually independent&#8221;. Note that <strong>Satoshi Onishi</strong> <strong>works for Shin-Etsu</strong>, so he&#8217;s independent as in he&#8217;s representing his company&#8217;s JV with Soitec. He is not a big player. In <strong>Shuo Zhang&#8217;s </strong>case<strong>,</strong> I cannot make any meaningful connections to anyone else. <strong>Paul Boudre</strong> of course is the outgoing CEO. Notice that he does not sit on any important committees. </p><p><strong>That brings me to Team China.</strong> Team China is the NSIG (National Silicon Industry Group) block, which invested 14.5% at the time which now is diluted to 10.34% stake (this is lower now) into Soitec in May 2016. NSIG, like many large Chinese firms, is an extension of the CCP. They hold two seats that I represent in Red. <strong>Kai Seikku</strong> is actually sitting on the powerful committees, aka the nomination and compensation committees. But importantly <strong>Jeffrey Wang</strong> has been pushed out to the not-important audit committee.</p><p><strong>Last is Team France.</strong> With the exception of <strong>Francoise Chombar</strong>, they are all French Nationals. I put <strong>Francoise Chombar</strong> on Team France because she shares a board with <strong>Eric Meurice</strong> at <strong>Umicore</strong>, so I assume she&#8217;s on his team. </p><p>Everyone else either works for <strong>CEA (French Alternative Energies and Atomic Energy Commission)</strong> or <strong>Bpifrance (French Public Investment Bank)</strong>, formerly worked there, or suspiciously looks connected (<strong>Laurence Delpy</strong> is clearly important but I have no links other than she worked at Alcatel Lucent where Pierre is from). <strong>Thierry Sommelet</strong> works at Bpifrance for example. </p><p>Importantly Team France consists of 6 out of 8 members of both of the most powerful Nomination and Compensation committees. And everyone else who is not affiliated with Team France conveniently sits outside of these boards with the exception of Kai Seikku, who represents the powerful ~10.34% share block from NSIG. Team France is clearly in control here, and the BPI and CEA seats are permanent, with rotating members but consistent committees. </p><p>What I&#8217;m trying to say is that Soitec&#8217;s board is controlled board by a very small number of players, all of which can be linked to France. Obviously, these members want to protect the interests of France, and what&#8217;s more most of the moves taken by the board pre-date Eric&#8217;s arrival. So it&#8217;s clearly not Eric in charge, but rather the representatives of France that are driving this bus!</p><h2>What&#8217;s France Got to Do With It?</h2><p>When I first started down the rabbit hole of the Eric Meurice takeover I thought the motivation was pretty simple. Ousted CEO Eric Meurice was looking for another kingdom to rule and found it in the form of Soitec. A clear power play, as highlighted by the management letter. After all, we knew he already had ambitions to sit in the CEO seat again, <a href="https://www.electronicsweekly.com/news/business/eric-meurice-favourite-take-st-2017-02/">per this ST Micro rumor</a>. In a series of successive moves, he rose from Director to Chairman, and he pushed his way to the top. </p><p>There are a few problems with that theory and it comes in two bold flavors. First, the year (July 2018) that Eric Meurice got appointed to the board as a director was the first year of expanded extraordinary resolutions. The previous year it went from 8 total resolutions to whopping 23 new resolutions. <strong>So the expanded board powers actually pre-date Eric&#8217;s arrival on the board</strong>. Eric Meurice was just the conduit for the control of the board. </p><p>The second thing was this extremely crucial disclosure about a standstill agreement with NSIG that made clued me in that something else was happening<strong>. When NSIG (National Silicon Industry Group aka China) bought the 14.5% stake in Soitec, they agreed to a standstill agreement on the shares.</strong></p><p><strong>The standstill agreement is an agreement at the time so that NSIG (China) didn&#8217;t continue to raise their stake in Soitec and effectively take over the company</strong>. It&#8217;s a takeover provision that stopped their large influence from increasing. The French board members were clearly aware of this. </p><p>But that standstill agreement ended on June 7, 2019, which was 1 year after Eric&#8217;s rise to power. This explains why he entered when he did. However, this tidbit made everything become clear(er) regarding the resolutions. </p><blockquote><p><strong>Should NSIG Sunrise S.&#224;.r.l acquire shares in the Company before</strong> the expiration of the Shareholders&#8217; Agreement at the close of the Shareholders&#8217; General Meeting called to approve the &#64257;nancial statements for the &#64257;scal year ended <strong>March 31, 2021, it would lose its rights relating to the Company&#8217;s governance</strong></p></blockquote><p>Team France knew they needed to lock down the company from a governance standpoint before March 31, 2021, or risk further influence from NSIG aka China. And Eric Meurice was the perfect man for the job. Win-win. </p><p>Besides Paul Boudre was ready to go. He terminated a paused employment contract so that the company wouldn&#8217;t have to pay him a termination fee, and they rewarded him with an incentive (I find this weird). He clearly signaled he was on the way out. Readers of the filings could have spotted his retirement as early as 2020, it was just the executive team that was blindsided. </p><p>But that brings us to what really happened. France Nationalized Soitec through a series of board moves, just in time before the Chinese government could push for more control. The CEO put in place is just a placeholder for the board.  </p><h2>National Champions Need Nationalization</h2><p>How are we surprised that France wanted to nationalize Soitec?! This is France we are talking about here! It&#8217;s clear that there&#8217;s a vested interest in keeping Soitec French-controlled. The expanded board powers also expanded government influence over Soitec. <strong>Soitec has effectively become a State <s>Owned</s> Controlled Enterprise.</strong>  </p><p>Look at the shareholder base. The ~17.67% French-controlled block was large, but not completely dominant given the large NSIG (aka China) block. A Chinese takeover of France&#8217;s semiconductor star would be devastating (not to mention embarrassing). Team France could not let this happen.  </p><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Faa6c6074-0903-4dc8-bb17-42c4737dc195_1215x926.png"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Faa6c6074-0903-4dc8-bb17-42c4737dc195_1215x926.png" width="622" height="473.8509090909091" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/aa6c6074-0903-4dc8-bb17-42c4737dc195_1215x926.png&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:838,&quot;width&quot;:1100,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:622,&quot;bytes&quot;:246525,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt=""></a></figure></div><p>All of the board actions in conjunction means that this was likely premeditated by the controlling shareholders - the state of France - to further control Soitec. Paul&#8217;s retirement was just the catalyst to push the changes that have already been made ahead. So what about our underqualified CEO candidate, Pierre Barnabe?</p><p>The thing that I found really curious was that <a href="https://www.inria.fr/en/inrias-board-directors">Pierre is on the board of INRIA</a>, or the Institute for Research in Computer Science and Automation. It&#8217;s a government lead entity that&#8217;s core purpose is to further France&#8217;s technology interests. From the French National control lens, Pierre is a perfect CEO. </p><h1>What Now?</h1><p>So now France effectively owns Soitec. What are they going to do with it? Paul left the company on a strong financial note and Soitec is a springboard for other national pursuits, <a href="https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/automotive-semiconductors-evs-and">like manufacturing Silicon Carbide</a>. Manufacturing Silicon Carbide would be terrible for Soitec the business, but great for France&#8217;s national ambitions. </p><p>Another likely option is that the board can use its expanded powers to purchase a fab in Europe, which would be perfect given Soitec produces wafers. Now France produces wafers and chips! There is a small design team within Soitec, and expanding that could also further French national interests. That&#8217;s a full stack semiconductor company with just 2 additional acquisitions.  </p><p>All of this makes sense in the now geopolitically driven world of semiconductors. As of late, there have been multiple announcements for new mega-fabs, <a href="https://time.com/6140476/intel-building-factory-ohio/">like the Intel Ohio fab</a> or the new <a href="https://pr.tsmc.com/english/news/2880">TSMC Japan fab</a>. Every country is doing what it can to shore up its semiconductor businesses, and <strong>France couldn&#8217;t let China steal their national champion.</strong>  </p><h2>Conclusions and Questions</h2><p>Soitec is effectively nationalized through board control. It makes sense given that China had a window to push for control, so instead, France just took the whole thing. France, Soitec&#8217;s largest shareholder, put everyone in a place of power in order to achieve this. What looked like a power-hungry move by a single actor, Eric Meurice, really was a coordinated win-win to control the company for France. </p><p>While I&#8217;m sure Soitec&#8217;s nationalization will be disappointing for free-market capitalists (where they at?), it&#8217;s not surprising at all given the current semiconductor climate. It&#8217;s a de facto-controlled company now. The takeaway: national-level politics continue to matter in the semiconductor industry. This theme is not going to go away any time soon. Soitec is just the latest and greatest in the series. <strong>Goodbye Soitec, Hello French National Semiconductor company.</strong></p><p>There are some loose ends. How does NSIG feel about this? Did Paul Boudre know about any of this? There are a lot of other interesting threads in this entire story, but it&#8217;s clear what happened. France nationalized their largest semiconductor company!</p><div><hr></div><p>If you enjoyed this piece, please consider subscribing. Even the free tier gets occasional posts. I try to write about semiconductor companies broadly from an investment perspective, so this investigative journalism is a bit different.</p><p class="button-wrapper" data-attrs="{&quot;url&quot;:&quot;https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/subscribe?&quot;,&quot;text&quot;:&quot;Subscribe now&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:null,&quot;class&quot;:null}"><a class="button primary" href="https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/subscribe?"><span>Subscribe now</span></a></p><p><strong>Oh by the way if you are either a past ASML employee during Eric&#8217;s time at ASML or a current Soitec employee who would love to talk, you can reach me at Doug@fabricatedknowledge.com.</strong> </p><div><hr></div><h2>Some Unfinished Business</h2><p>I wanted to discuss parts of the story that didn&#8217;t flow well with the rest of the power politics at Soitec. The question I presume most people would be wondering is about Pierre Barnabe. Why is he not qualified again? </p><p>I really had a problem with this statement from Soitec management. </p><blockquote><p><em>He draws upon a remarkable track record that includes a threefold revenue increase at the</em> <em>Atos</em> <em>Big Data and Cybersecurity</em> <em>division in the space of a few years, in a highly competitive market requiring deep</em> <em>cooperation with the ecosystem.</em> </p></blockquote><p>Part of that three-fold growth was <a href="https://www.crunchbase.com/search/acquisitions/field/organizations/num_acquisitions/atos">38 acquisitions</a> along the way. Is that execution or is that just buying three times more revenue? And also the stock and business are horrid. It&#8217;s down 63% over the last 5 years and revenue growth is tepid at best.</p><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F3c8829b4-01b9-4600-a02f-4e6a2abe7af1_686x503.png"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F3c8829b4-01b9-4600-a02f-4e6a2abe7af1_686x503.png" width="686" height="503" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/3c8829b4-01b9-4600-a02f-4e6a2abe7af1_686x503.png&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:503,&quot;width&quot;:686,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:39850,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt=""></a></figure></div><p>Oh, and STMicroelectronics has a deep bench of French National semiconductor executives that would have made a perfect fit. Given Pierres in with the government, Pierre definitely did not get the job on the basis of merit. </p><h2>What about Paul Boudre? </h2><p>One of the weirdest side exits is Paul Boudre. By voluntarily abdicating his contract agreement and then getting paid to do so, I think Paul had wind of changes but didn&#8217;t care as he knew he was on the way out. And even if Paul did want to change things, he was locked out of the committees that matter (compensation and nomination). He wouldn&#8217;t be privy to what happened anyways.</p><p>I think the biggest blindside is the executive committee. I get why their reaction is so strong, but I think their outrage of Paul&#8217;s replacement and the lack of internal promotion is missing the bigger national interest story in what they thought would be a routine succession. The COO likely expected promotion, and other executives in turn would be promoted to COO. I feel bad for them, as it&#8217;s frustrating to not be a part of the company they clearly helped build. </p><div><hr></div><h2>Appendix: A bit more on SOI</h2><p>Silicon on Insulator is a technology that embeds the insulator below the surface of silicon. Usually, this is done via Ion implantation, a &#8220;smart cut&#8221; and a flip of the substrate so that the buried insulator is now below a device layer. This improves overall performance meaningfully.</p><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F910065c4-d914-45a5-bb09-8c730be79f7d_1353x509.png"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F910065c4-d914-45a5-bb09-8c730be79f7d_1353x509.png" width="1100" height="414" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/910065c4-d914-45a5-bb09-8c730be79f7d_1353x509.png&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:414,&quot;width&quot;:1100,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:134176,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt=""></a></figure></div><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb144a6d7-253e-4aa2-aebd-d9083df098d3_1363x759.png"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb144a6d7-253e-4aa2-aebd-d9083df098d3_1363x759.png" width="1100" height="613" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/b144a6d7-253e-4aa2-aebd-d9083df098d3_1363x759.png&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:613,&quot;width&quot;:1100,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:285250,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt=""></a></figure></div><p>Soitec is the only volume manufacturer in the world, and their competitors license their technology. Soitec believes that their market share in SOI wafers is ~77% globally. </p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[TSMC Earnings - The Handoff from Mobile to HPC]]></title><description><![CDATA[2022 will be the year datacenter takes front and center at TSMC]]></description><link>https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/tsmc-earnings-the-handoff-from-mobile</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/tsmc-earnings-the-handoff-from-mobile</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Doug (mule)]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 13 Jan 2022 17:35:44 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/ea979c84-641d-4abb-99c0-3fd305a3b7ff_5026x3338.jpeg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Hello! The most important semiconductor company in the world reported earnings last night. It&#8217;s been something of a tradition to post Taiwan Semiconductor Company (TSMC) earnings posts not behind my paywall, and I think that I&#8217;m going to continue that to kickoff each earnings season. </p><p>There are so many threads in the TSMC call that I want to talk about, but the big one that I think we will look back on 2022 for TSMC is that this is the year HPC will become the largest part of the business. Let&#8217;s expand. </p><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fc9a34855-deed-40fb-904d-95104dc445a6_1480x672.png"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fc9a34855-deed-40fb-904d-95104dc445a6_1480x672.png" width="1100" height="499" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/c9a34855-deed-40fb-904d-95104dc445a6_1480x672.png&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:499,&quot;width&quot;:1100,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:95250,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt=""></a><figcaption class="image-caption">TSMC&#8217;s current business mix</figcaption></figure></div><p>Smartphones and HPC are neck and neck in the largest buckets for TSMC, but HPC is growing faster. The reason for sluggish smartphone growth was laid out pretty well by TSMC, and that&#8217;s volume growth in smartphones has topped out.</p><blockquote><p>Yes, I think -- let me add. The global smartphone unit growth last year is about 6%. So some of the -- you see some of the company smartphone revenue may grow, it could be due to the pricing. But we -- our pricing strategy, as you understand, is strategic, not optimistic. So we'll grow with the smartphone units in our business. </p></blockquote><p>Well TSMC just guided for &#8220;high 20s&#8221; growth, and long-term growth of 15-20% CAGR. They additionally guided to an accelerating 2022, and strong sequential growth into Q1. Given that they think that their business will grow in-line smartphone units, the only logical growth driver is HPC. I did some pretty simple math to back out what the HPC segment should look like given their assumptions on growth. </p><blockquote><p>Let me answer the platform question. In 2022, <strong>we expect the HPC and automotive to grow faster than the corporate average. IoT, similar</strong>. Smartphones close to the corporate average. That's the platform growth.</p></blockquote><p>I&#8217;m a bit more bearish on smartphones growing 20%+ unit growth so let&#8217;s say smartphones grow at 15% next year, and DCE / Other grows at 10% as well. I grew automotive at 50% and IoT at ~28% - and the result is that HPC revenue crosses over smartphones in 2022. I use HPC revenue as the plug to then hit the ~28% revenue number. It looks like this is the year HPC is finally larger than Smartphones at TSMC. </p><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F8a0d4dfc-b853-435d-878f-0dd132c8a5c1_775x182.png"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F8a0d4dfc-b853-435d-878f-0dd132c8a5c1_775x182.png" width="775" height="182" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/8a0d4dfc-b853-435d-878f-0dd132c8a5c1_775x182.png&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:182,&quot;width&quot;:775,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:20373,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt=""></a></figure></div><p>For the longest time, I have believed that the largest incremental dollar pool of revenue growth will be HPC. It&#8217;s nice to see it come true and TSMC confirms that this is their belief as well. I first wrote about when I suspected meaningful growth in the data center in 2022 <a href="https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/facebooks-spending-spree-semicap">after Facebook&#8217;s earnings</a>. I got it confirmed shortly thereafter by <a href="https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/on-semi-and-nxpi-alchip-onto-and">AIchip&#8217;s results</a>. I had a suspicion that data center would be strong, but hearing the largest fab in the world expect something akin to ~40%+ growth in this segment is pretty mind-boggling even to a huge bull like me. </p><p>Another point to the leadership of the data center going forward is that HPC is starting to adopt the smaller nodes faster than smartphones, which used to be the premier first adopters of TSMC&#8217;s newest node. In the past, HPC would adopt the newest node a year after smartphone, but now HPC is in the driver seat and will be adopting N3 at the same time smartphone is. Beyond just node adoption, I&#8217;m pretty bullish on data center exposed stocks like Marvell and Nvidia. </p><p>Speaking of Marvell and Nvidia one of the questions on the call was  &#8220;how can you grow your revenue faster than your fabless customer&#8217;s expected revenue growth&#8221;. TSMC answered that they believe it&#8217;s pricing and share gains.</p><blockquote><p>This is C.C. Wei. Actually, the growth in 2022 is all the above you just mentioned. It's a share gain, it's the pricing and also its a unit growth. Did I answer your question?</p></blockquote><p>Part of this is that Intel is starting to outsource to TSMC and that foundry likely will grow faster than memory this year. <strong>But I have a hard time believing another obvious answer is that the fabless estimates are too low.</strong> </p><p>Given that TSMC just guided to accelerating revenue (25% 2021 growth to 28%+ 2022 growth) and has over 50% of global market share, I have a hard time believing that the industry is going to meaningfully decelerate while TSMC revenue explodes. The numbers don&#8217;t reconcile. And that is why I believe that the fabless companies&#8217; revenue estimates are likely a bit too low. Also that their 9% industry growth number is likely too low. Getting the theme here?</p><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fa4d1e981-6668-48f4-a728-570cbbaf9766_1061x538.png"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fa4d1e981-6668-48f4-a728-570cbbaf9766_1061x538.png" width="1061" height="538" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/a4d1e981-6668-48f4-a728-570cbbaf9766_1061x538.png&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:538,&quot;width&quot;:1061,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:27719,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt=""></a></figure></div><p>I believe that 2022 is going to be another strong year, and that almost every fabless company&#8217;s numbers will be revised higher. Let&#8217;s turn next to the capex side of the equation. </p><h2><strong>TSMC Expects to Spend $40-44B on Capex</strong></h2><p>Not only was growing faster for longer a surprise but the $40-44b capex was a real shocker. For context, the most bullish estimate on the street was at ~$40 billion. The upside is now the new downside case. Given that WFE grew by ~40% last year, and TSMC grew capex by ~77% in 2021 over 2020, this is pretty meaningful growth. In absolute terms, they are adding more spending in 2022 than in 2021. But of course, this is a deceleration on a larger base. </p><p>I think that the preliminary read-through is that WFE is going to have yet another good year. I believe that WFE likely is more to the tune of 20% growth than to 10% growth. Speaking of 10% growth - <a href="https://www.semi.org/en/news-media-press-releases/global-fab-equipment-spending-projected-to-log-record-high-in-2022-to-mark-third-consecutive-year-of-growth-semi-reports">this estimate by SEMI</a> came out on January 11th called for 10% growth and after TSMC&#8217;s spending estimates it already seems like this will be false. 2 days and it&#8217;s already out of date! The true number is going to be higher.</p><p>As we discussed on the <a href="https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/tsmc-and-ase-december-results-asml">VLSI semicap comparison of numbers bottom-up to top-down</a>, it seems like estimates need to move higher. I think this is great for semicap broadly (surprise!). If you&#8217;re a long-time reader of the substack, one of the core beliefs is that the rising capital intensity of making a semiconductor accretes to fabs and even more so to semicap companies (ASML, LRCX, AMAT, KLAC, TOELY, etc). </p><p>This is just another indication that the thesis is correct given that Capex is growing faster than revenue. Which brings me to an interesting question - how could TSMC ever support this kind of spending indefinitely? The answer is that they are either utterly wrong about their growth and are going to throw the entire market into overcapacity, or that demand is still being underestimated. I believe that it&#8217;s the latter, as I wrote in my <a href="https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/in-the-middle-of-transition-2022">cyclical to the secular thought experiment</a>. I believe that TSMC believes this as well, and given how they are investing and guiding, I want to call this TSMC&#8217;s bold bet. </p><h2>Growing for Longer - TSMC&#8217;s Bold Bet</h2><p>A recurring theme of the analysts calls with TSMC is that every quarter analysts pepper management with &#8220;how can you maintain the margin with this investment?&#8221; and &#8220;you&#8217;re spending a lot on capex will this ever normalize?&#8221; questions. The answer that TSMC answers each quarter is somewhere along the lines of &#8220;We are going to grow trust us&#8221;. This first long-term guidance in a while is an indication of that. </p><blockquote><p>We expect our long-term revenue to be between 15% and 20% CAGR over the next several years in U.S. dollar terms, of course, fueled by all 4 growth platform which are smartphone, HPC, IoT and automotive.</p></blockquote><p><strong>The staggering thing I want to point out to you is their 10-year revenue growth CAGR is 14%</strong>. That&#8217;s the kind of growth that got them to the largest fab in the industry, yet their long-term revenue guide is now actually a call that their revenue will accelerate on a larger base. It&#8217;s impossible for them to gain share at the rate they used to so the only answer is the entire industry must accelerate as well. </p><p>TSMC is probably one of the best management teams in the entire industry with the most credibility you can ask for. They are prudent, ROIC focused, conservative in their node shrinks yet aggressive in their capital spending<strong>.</strong> <strong>Simply put</strong> <strong>they do not miss</strong>. If they are investing in larger amounts for accelerating growth they believe will come, I am going to believe them. </p><p>This is the definition of long-term thinking and bold bets. They are pushing forward at an even faster pace at the peak of their dominance in order to ensure they continue to hold share. And everything is pointing to the diversity and strength of the entire semiconductor ecosystem, and I think that the answer is clear. The 2020s are going to be a better decade than the one before it for the entire semiconductor ecosystem. </p><h2>Passing Price</h2><p>I want to briefly mention the gross margin part of the equation. Every quarter there is a lot of hang wringing about the sustainability of the gross margin at TSMC. Last quarter analysts got really hung up on &#8220;51% or greater&#8221; long-term margins and asked in as many ways as possible if that margin was sustainable.</p><p>This quarter of course they put up 53% gross margin and now are guiding to &#8220;53% or greater&#8221; margin longer term. The bar of course has shifted higher. The right answer and framing around the gross margin sustainability debate are that TSMC really is one of the only games in town, and the demand for their capacity is intense. I mentioned briefly that TSMC can just pass price as much as they want in the <a href="https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/the-rising-tide-of-semiconductor">Rising Tide of Semiconductor Costs</a> and I think that will continue. </p><p>No matter how much capex spend is required and how much depreciation and amortization will grow as a part of TSMC&#8217;s cost, TSMC is simply not a price taker. They will raise prices and pass their costs onto their customers, and in this case, it seems like they are able to pass on more than just the cost they take. If they can maintain 53%+ margins against rising CoGs, this means that customers will be taking price raises on the chin. Because what other choice do they really have? Intel&#8217;s Foundry business is still more of an idea more than a meaningful business, and Samsung is growing but relatively small. TSMC will get the money that they are due. </p><div><hr></div><p class="button-wrapper" data-attrs="{&quot;url&quot;:&quot;https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/subscribe?&quot;,&quot;text&quot;:&quot;Subscribe now&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:null,&quot;class&quot;:null}"><a class="button primary" href="https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/subscribe?"><span>Subscribe now</span></a></p><p>There&#8217;s a lot more in the transcript itself, which I recommend reading if you have some time. TSMC continues to believe I think that the continued prepayments by their customers are another indication that the fabless companies get it as well. They want more capacity because their businesses are well but they are capacity constrained. </p><p>An interesting idea I had was that the capacity precommitments in order to secure capacity feels a bit like the ASML investment by INTC / TSMC. It&#8217;s clearly a greater good, there is really only one company that can achieve it, and it&#8217;s going to cost a lot of money. In order for the economics to work at TSMC will need a lot of money. </p><div class="tweet" data-attrs="{&quot;url&quot;:&quot;https://twitter.com/_fabknowledge_/status/1481622084891541508&quot;,&quot;full_text&quot;:&quot;There is a real chance that we look back at the TSM capacity commitments from their customers akin to EUV commitments from INTC/TSM when ASML was struggling to ramp. A communal good that must be paid for in order to secure the future and paid by everyone.&quot;,&quot;username&quot;:&quot;_fabknowledge_&quot;,&quot;name&quot;:&quot;Fabricated Knowledge&quot;,&quot;date&quot;:&quot;Thu Jan 13 13:40:06 +0000 2022&quot;,&quot;photos&quot;:[],&quot;quoted_tweet&quot;:{},&quot;retweet_count&quot;:0,&quot;like_count&quot;:6,&quot;expanded_url&quot;:{},&quot;video_url&quot;:null}"><a href="https://twitter.com/_fabknowledge_/status/1481622084891541508" target="_blank"><div class="tweet-header"><img class="tweet-user-avatar" src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/twitter_name/w_36/_fabknowledge_.jpg" alt="Twitter avatar for @_fabknowledge_"><span class="tweet-author-name">Fabricated Knowledge </span><span class="tweet-author">@_fabknowledge_</span></div>There is a real chance that we look back at the TSM capacity commitments from their customers akin to EUV commitments from INTC/TSM when ASML was struggling to ramp. A communal good that must be paid for in order to secure the future and paid by everyone.</a><a href="https://twitter.com/_fabknowledge_/status/1481622084891541508" target="_blank"><div class="tweet-footer"><p class="tweet-date">January 13th 2022</p><span class="likes"><span class="like-count">6</span> Likes</span></div></a></div><p>Anyways that&#8217;s it for today. I just wanted to cover these points for now, and I&#8217;ll be posting a lot more content like this but for the ~100s of other semiconductor companies that will be reporting in the next month. I just always love to start with the biggest and baddest first. </p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[TSMC and ASE December Results, ASML Fires, and Semicap Estimates Are Too Low]]></title><description><![CDATA[A quick update and a lesson in acceleration and deceleration of revenue]]></description><link>https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/tsmc-and-ase-december-results-asml</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/tsmc-and-ase-december-results-asml</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Doug (mule)]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 12 Jan 2022 17:02:45 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/h_600,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F95be5c52-410d-4634-a2db-d975a2477ecb_1171x650.png" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[
      <p>
          <a href="https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/tsmc-and-ase-december-results-asml">
              Read more
          </a>
      </p>
   ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[In the Middle of Transition: 2022 Semiconductor Outlook ]]></title><description><![CDATA[What would the shift from cyclical to secular look like?]]></description><link>https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/in-the-middle-of-transition-2022</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/in-the-middle-of-transition-2022</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Doug (mule)]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 06 Jan 2022 15:28:03 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/h_600,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb89c1085-e082-470d-92b0-b5e2ed844ec7_1024x895.png" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A strongly held belief I have is that semiconductors are in the middle of a new golden age. I think that most of my readers would agree. But something that&#8217;s always concerned investors is the industry&#8217;s cyclicality. Of course, it worries me, too, but as the &#8220;chip shortage&#8221; has gone on longer and longer I&#8217;ve pretty much concluded that no one knows when it will end, and in many ways, this would be exactly what the shift from a cyclical industry to a secular market would look like. Let me explain.</p><p>The semiconductor market for years has been characterized by booms and busts. Below is a handy long-term graph of revenue growth. I added the black line as emphasis for 0% YoY growth, meaning if the red line is above the axis, revenue expands, but if it&#8217;s below, it contracts. Historically, the boom-bust cycles are primarily driven by supply.</p><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb89c1085-e082-470d-92b0-b5e2ed844ec7_1024x895.png"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb89c1085-e082-470d-92b0-b5e2ed844ec7_1024x895.png" width="1024" height="895" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/b89c1085-e082-470d-92b0-b5e2ed844ec7_1024x895.png&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:895,&quot;width&quot;:1024,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt=""></a><figcaption class="image-caption"><em><a href="https://www.semiconductors.org/global-semiconductor-sales-increase-24-year-to-year-in-october-annual-sales-projected-to-increase-26-in-2021-exceed-600-billion-in-2022/">https://www.semiconductors.org/global-semiconductor-sales-increase-24-year-to-year-in-october-annual-sales-projected-to-increase-26-in-2021-exceed-600-billion-in-2022/</a></em></figcaption></figure></div><p>The core reason for this is that capacity additions are extremely lumpy and adding new capacity via a fab came with huge fixed costs, and then very low variable costs, especially in sub-sectors like memory. The incentives were obvious. If you had a new fab, you could use your marginal cost advantage to offer a cheaper product and, in the process, blow up the total profit pool. In many ways, this was the story of the ~80s-90s memory market. The YoY numbers from that time make the ~2000-2002 wobble look tame. The wild fluctuations on this log chart of memory prices pretty much tell the entire story, with dozens of companies adding capacity and massive benefits from each new technology generation in terms of capacity.</p><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F111a2bc8-ed9c-4f68-97b1-9f7a494b9319_994x708.jpeg"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F111a2bc8-ed9c-4f68-97b1-9f7a494b9319_994x708.jpeg" width="994" height="708" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/111a2bc8-ed9c-4f68-97b1-9f7a494b9319_994x708.jpeg&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:708,&quot;width&quot;:994,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt=""></a><figcaption class="image-caption"><em><a href="https://www.jcmit.net/mem2015.htm">https://www.jcmit.net/mem2015.htm</a></em></figcaption></figure></div><p>But of course, things changed. Moore&#8217;s law slowed down and <a href="https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/the-rising-tide-of-semiconductor">the rising cost</a> of making semiconductors from both the fabrication and <a href="https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/the-tech-monopolies-go-vertical">design perspective</a> has forced consolidation and more rational industry competition. Why blow up the profit pool of your entire industry when the magnitude of costs is reaching tens of billions of dollars? Why not add capacity in a more disciplined manner given that you know what your competitors are doing? This is exactly what&#8217;s happening in memory, the most hyper-cyclical part of the industry. Most of the more mature semiconductor segments have already started to focus on their own product fiefdoms. With little competition head to head and only at the margins. Consolidation also helped quite a bit.</p><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F02d1aaed-0dc7-4253-a57b-fbc4123d8e7c_2106x1154.jpeg"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F02d1aaed-0dc7-4253-a57b-fbc4123d8e7c_2106x1154.jpeg" width="1100" height="603" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/02d1aaed-0dc7-4253-a57b-fbc4123d8e7c_2106x1154.jpeg&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:603,&quot;width&quot;:1100,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:&quot;Image&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt="Image" title="Image"></a></figure></div><p>Another large driver as software eating the world and semiconductors being used in more and larger parts of the economy. Our cars and our homes took more semiconductors, and of course, our phones became much more integral parts of our lives. We went from essentially one market in the 1990s (PCs) to multiple end markets today. My favorite chart&nbsp;of the different vibrant end-markets came from the ASML investor day in 2021:</p><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fe66cca81-363c-4f93-ad01-7bdf11db3690_882x504.png"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fe66cca81-363c-4f93-ad01-7bdf11db3690_882x504.png" width="882" height="504" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/e66cca81-363c-4f93-ad01-7bdf11db3690_882x504.png&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:504,&quot;width&quot;:882,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:247232,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt=""></a></figure></div><p>The important thing is that each of these cycles are happening independently. For example, phones are starting to slow down in volume as the average life of a phone increases, while <a href="https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/the-digital-transformation-of-cars">automotive companies are just starting to ramp EV and ADAS content in their cars</a>.</p><p>This is a simple expression of the law of large numbers. If semiconductors have a positive growth relationship it would mean that the bigger the number of different markets that are not correlated, the closer the aggregate results will approach the underlying trend. Each new diversifier will lower the volatility of just a single market&#8217;s results. I think that&#8217;s happening today.</p><p>So back to the path of cyclical to secular growth and what it would look like. Especially for a cyclical industry, each time there&#8217;s a year of sustained strong results there&#8217;s an expectation of a reversal to the mean. As bullish as I am, I don&#8217;t have the guts to say, &#8220;growth only, no down years.&#8221; That kind of statement is insane to make if you&#8217;re in the business of having reasonable accurate projections given the historical base rate.</p><p>But right now, we have clear indications of new demand streams from AI, new industries, and the broader slowing of Moore&#8217;s law. We also have more disciplined and consolidated supply, and despite the crazy capacity additions that have already taken place, the industry continues to grow. Semiconductors seem to have swapped from a supply-driven industry to a demand-driven industry since the pandemic. That, to me, is the big key of what the cyclical-to-secular market would look like. Additionally, semiconductors actually grew through a recession, which is pretty telling for the secular argument.</p><p><strong>If there were ever a scenario of an historically cyclical and supply-driven market shifting into a secularly growing, demand-driven market, we&#8217;re living in it.</strong> Students of history know that each year there should be a supply-driven correction at some point, but each year the balance of supply and demand looks to be in demand&#8217;s favor. So, while we think that the continued and consistent supply additions will eventually turn the market, demand continues to outweigh supply additions.</p><p><strong>If this sounds familiar, it&#8217;s because it&#8217;s pretty much the regime we&#8217;ve been living under since 2020. </strong>The chip shortage was originally expected to abate or turn around by the end of 2021 and that looks like it won&#8217;t happen. Now it&#8217;s expected to end in 2023, but it&#8217;s not like there hasn&#8217;t been a huge capacity addition since last year. The supply-demand crossover always seems to be just one year away. What&#8217;s happening? Why haven&#8217;t the recent capacity additions relieved the supply-chain crisis? An exchange that I thought was pretty enlightening was this conversation on the Q3 2021 ASML earnings call, answering an analyst&#8217;s question:</p><p><em>Yes, Sandeep. I mean you've been around a long time and you asked the million-dollar question. So &#8212; and the real answer is we don't know. We have some indications and some ideas. And yes, you are absolutely right, the wafer out capacity today is a big &#8212; is a lot larger than it was in Q4 2020. That's true. And still, we see these shortages. Now I spoke to a very large customer and basically asked the same question.</em></p><p><em>And I actually said, Peter, we don't know either. <strong>Because somehow we haven't been able to connect all the dots that actually are the underlying drivers for this demand.</strong></em></p><p>This sounds like an anecdote in favor of the shift towards a demand-driven market. Each year, massive supply is added, yet demand continues to simply outweigh it. That would be what the &#8220;secular growth&#8221; case would look like for me, and in some ways we&#8217;re in the perfect expression of that transition. We&#8217;re in the middle of it.</p><p>Now, to be clear, I&#8217;m a student of history and not irrational enough to call the end of the booms and bust in the semiconductor market. <strong>There&#8217;s just no way I can make that call in good conscience! But I think it could happen at, say, a ~30% probability, and in many ways, we&#8217;re doing the things that would be needed for this to happen. I just want to highlight that if the shift were to occur, it would look almost exactly like what&#8217;s happening today.</strong></p><p>We&#8217;ll just have to wait and see. The visibility of the industry is one year at best, but the one-year forward expectations look pretty good to me. I think particularly driven by Datacenter, IoT, and Automotive, there&#8217;s a chance the industry could put up a historic double-digit growth year. That kind of sustained expansion is something we&#8217;ve never seen in the semiconductor markets of old. But if this really is the shift from cyclical to secular, this is what we should expect.</p><p>Anyways. <a href="https://zoom.us/rec/play/lkaZmYFLQ2IoUJGXVm1En5KxO-ESF4w0NPb8rnvnPwArPGbScNW8CzrgrM_DlED5P22eojb43dGclEs.LYleDcVshMyN_QTF?startTime=1641245464000&amp;_x_zm_rtaid=h-hrAVAYRgq9QvpuW4M3EA.1641418206610.7b7cfe812fcdf958064cb5f7a7d31b15&amp;_x_zm_rhtaid=406">I want to post a webinar of me and Dylan talking about the semiconductor markets by end market for 2022</a>. This is a bit of a more typical 2022 outlook if you ask me, but I wanted to add this one caveat that if semiconductors are really going to be a secularly growing industry, we&#8217;re clearly in the middle of what that transition would look like.</p><h1>Performance in 2021</h1><p>Without further ado let&#8217;s go into name-specific returns year-to-date and an overview of the space.</p><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F052880e8-f295-429f-bb45-b7f1b488b898_1226x724.png"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F052880e8-f295-429f-bb45-b7f1b488b898_1226x724.png" width="1100" height="650" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/052880e8-f295-429f-bb45-b7f1b488b898_1226x724.png&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:650,&quot;width&quot;:1100,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:47257,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt=""></a></figure></div><p>The best-performing stock this year was Synaptics. The worst was OLED. I&#8217;m not surprised at OLED, but I am surprised to see the absolute strength of everything &#8220;IoT&#8221;-related. Synaptics is primarily an IoT-related company, SITM to some extent is an IoT-related name, and so is Nordic Semi. Amba is an automotive name but also partially IoT. Getting the theme here?</p><p>On the loser side of the equation, some names I&#8217;m not that surprised to see are here: WOLF and Intel, to name a few, but additionally FSLR, SEDG, ENPH, and POWI. The first three names are solar-related, and 2020 was the wildest solar year ever, so a cooling-off period makes sense to me. I&#8217;m also kind of interested in these companies from that aspect. POWI was an expensive momentum-driven name, so no real surprises there. But beyond price return, how much of it was fundamental- versus multiple-driven?</p><h1>Valuations of the Space</h1><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd63e05bd-ddc9-4b52-b247-beecb3319ea8_1176x743.png"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd63e05bd-ddc9-4b52-b247-beecb3319ea8_1176x743.png" width="1100" height="695" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/d63e05bd-ddc9-4b52-b247-beecb3319ea8_1176x743.png&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:695,&quot;width&quot;:1100,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:40966,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt=""></a></figure></div><p>Most of the winners in terms of price were driven by multiple expansion, but a few names did benefit from mostly earnings-per-share growth &#8212; especially the worst performers. Companies that had positive EPS growth and negative price return in my opinion are likely the place to hunt for bargains next year. Companies that grew earnings faster than price this year include SITM, ON, MXL, AMKR, AMD, DIOD, LRCX, BESI, NXPI, STM:FP, MTSI, ALGM, MPWR, IFX:GR, MU, QCOM, ADI, MKSI, TXN, POWI, CRUS, WOLF, ENPH, SWKS, QRVO, FSLR, SEDG, and OLED.</p><p>From this list alone, you&#8217;d assume that <strong>Automotive, RFFE, and solar is the place to play</strong>. I think it&#8217;s not quite as simple as that. I would avoid RFFE and am starting to be interested in solar. That being said, I continue to believe that automotive has one of the best mixes of price and growth in the entire space, and the likes of ON, NXPI, STM, ALGM, IFX, ADI, and TXN are worth a second look.</p><p>I think that semiconductor stocks are in an okay place right now. I continue to love areas of well-priced secular growth relative to the market (Metrology!), but I continue to worry about lapping issues by the end of this year, especially in Semicap. I think that right now we&#8217;re hitting the hardest year-over-year comparisons for revenue growth and it&#8217;s hard to see acceleration from here. This is my &#8220;concern&#8221; broadly for semiconductor-related stocks and I believe that from a top-down perspective most companies should decelerate this year.</p><p>I would summarize by saying that 2021 was one of the best years fundamentally for semiconductor companies. Almost every company grew &#8211; and most grew much faster than the industry growth of 24%.</p><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F212178f3-6e15-48ec-bd2a-489c8d278ece_1582x863.png"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F212178f3-6e15-48ec-bd2a-489c8d278ece_1582x863.png" width="1100" height="600" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/212178f3-6e15-48ec-bd2a-489c8d278ece_1582x863.png&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:600,&quot;width&quot;:1100,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:45863,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt=""></a></figure></div><p>On top of that, certain companies managed to do much better on an EBIT growth basis. The average company&#8217;s margin expanded, which should be expected given high fixed costs. Certain companies&#8217; margins expanded meaningfully, like ON, MXL, SITM, and AMBA.</p><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F71c380c2-7031-40c9-b10e-c502a2e51b8f_1760x725.png"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F71c380c2-7031-40c9-b10e-c502a2e51b8f_1760x725.png" width="1100" height="453" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/71c380c2-7031-40c9-b10e-c502a2e51b8f_1760x725.png&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:453,&quot;width&quot;:1100,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:47280,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt=""></a></figure></div><p>By the way, I plan to start up the <a href="https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/february-semiconductor-monthly-roundup">&#8220;monthly stock price review,&#8221;</a> similar to the one I used to do before the hike. I really enjoyed writing those, mostly for myself, as it&#8217;s a way to systematically look at the entire universe. It helps be vigilant from a top-down perspective and make sure you&#8217;re not &#8220;missing anything.&#8221; &nbsp;Frankly, I missed some companies this year, and part of that was the transition of coming back after being gone for so long. No longer!</p><div><hr></div><p>Happy New Years, y&#8217;all! Here&#8217;s to a better year for us all. It&#8217;s been a good year for semiconductors, but I for one wish for a great year for all of us. 2020 of course was a rough year, and 2021, while marginally &#8220;better,&#8221; wasn&#8217;t the greatest. 2022 I hope is an opportunity for a great year for everyone. Stay healthy and safe! &nbsp;</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[2022 Semiconductor Webinar (and Outlook)]]></title><description><![CDATA[Something New is in the Works! Link Below!]]></description><link>https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/2022-semiconductor-webinar-and-outlook</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/2022-semiconductor-webinar-and-outlook</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Doug (mule)]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 31 Dec 2021 10:20:04 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/34a51195-f3ae-4bd9-96a8-26488679ec3b_1500x500.png" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Instead of writing up a <a href="https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/semiconductor-outlook-in-2021-its">long post like I did last year</a> - I am opting for something new this year. This year @Dylan552p of Semianalysis and I will be having a friendly conversation about what we think the 2022 semiconductor market will look like. I think this will also be the first episode of our cohosted Podcast that we plan to be launching shortly after! </p><p>A podcast sounds like great fun - and a great place to discuss a meaningful amount of the work I do that doesn&#8217;t make it into a weekly post. Whenever I put content into a weekly post - it&#8217;s usually well researched and pretty nuanced to a degree. I don&#8217;t like to put straight conjecture if I can help it - but that is where the podcast will differ.</p><p>The goal is to have new episodes bi-monthly - and mostly we will just have a nice chat about semiconductor news that happened over the last 2 weeks. I&#8217;m really looking forward to it - as it&#8217;s a formal project Dylan and I have been working on for some time. It&#8217;s been a blast to work with him more, we both push each other to do better. </p><p>Anyways - for those who are interested in listening to our first webinar which will eventually become the first podcast episode - <a href="https://zoom.us/webinar/register/6816408814501/WN_l_qpzwA3Tj2NRELy16p1UA">feel free to register for the webinar</a>. </p><p>https://zoom.us/webinar/register/6816408814501/WN_l_qpzwA3Tj2NRELy16p1UA</p><div><hr></div><p>P.S. I will be posting a 2022 Outlook post as a summary of the webinar. I also apologize for the lack of posts recently, I have been dragging my feet pushing out a 2022 Outlook piece, and then of course I got very sick for a few days. Instead, I decided to really focus on next year. I&#8217;m excited about what&#8217;s coming. Happy New Years Ya&#8217;ll! </p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Intel's Mobileye Stub and Positioning]]></title><description><![CDATA[Semis are not that crowded & I take a crack at valuing Intel (model attached)]]></description><link>https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/intels-mobileye-stub-and-positioning</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/intels-mobileye-stub-and-positioning</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Doug (mule)]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 19 Dec 2021 18:09:59 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/h_600,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F193c8195-2d6b-4047-a7c1-6f36912934ed_2400x1240.png" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Before we talk about Intel&#8217;s Mobileye announcement - I wanted to highlight something I&#8217;ve noticed in the semiconductor space. It&#8217;s been no secret there has been a large de-grossing (moving gross leverage down) in the market. In particular, many SMID cap companies are experiencing bear-market-like drawdowns while the indices are relatively unscathed. Large caps are leading, meaning that if you don&#8217;t own FAMNG - you are feeling pain. An example of this dynamic is <a href="https://twitter.com/CarterBWorth/status/1471124157417115661">highlighted by Carter Braxton</a>. </p><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F3e3c6a88-e792-4656-9574-7f77075f961c_819x900.jpeg"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F3e3c6a88-e792-4656-9574-7f77075f961c_819x900.jpeg" width="414" height="454.94505494505495" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/3e3c6a88-e792-4656-9574-7f77075f961c_819x900.jpeg&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:900,&quot;width&quot;:819,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:414,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:&quot;Image&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt="Image" title="Image"></a><figcaption class="image-caption">Don&#8217;t kill me if the data is wrong - but I believe it&#8217;s directional</figcaption></figure></div><h2>Positioning</h2><p>Probably one of the hardest-hit places right now is SaaS - where a huge run since 2019 has kept this sector extremely popular among funds. Meanwhile, many hedge funds were looking to short anything and started to short semiconductors on DRAM price weakness and a single month of smartphone weakness in China.</p><p>As funds deleveraged, the crowded longs were sold and the crowded shorts were bought back. The results of the deleverage were drastic, and best summarized in this chart below comparing software to hardware returns YTD. </p><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F193c8195-2d6b-4047-a7c1-6f36912934ed_2400x1240.png"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F193c8195-2d6b-4047-a7c1-6f36912934ed_2400x1240.png" width="1100" height="568" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/193c8195-2d6b-4047-a7c1-6f36912934ed_2400x1240.png&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:568,&quot;width&quot;:1100,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt=""></a></figure></div><p>I want to caution you - this is not a sustainable trend. I usually don&#8217;t see a deleveraging and say &#8220;this is wonderful for my stocks!&#8221; - but rather take a step back and wonder if this is good at all. Usually, there&#8217;s some kind of snapback to the previous regime, and in my view, I think that Semiconductor stocks could have a bit of a cooling-off period here. Thursday&#8217;s relative performance seems to indicate that.  </p><p>But the real value of the deleveraging is the litmus test for the crowdedness of the sector - and I&#8217;m happy to say with the exception of maybe Nvidia - semiconductors are anything but crowded. My biggest fear about semis is that the themes I write about are more crowded and appreciated than I thought - which in turn could make the forward results poor. </p><p>The positioning tells us that some investors still do not buy the secular story of semiconductors - and that&#8217;s great! The results should prove themselves, and when eventually Mr. Market falls in love with semiconductors, even the skeptics will be interested. </p><p>I liken it to the regime change that has happened in the last 5 years within software stocks - where software went from a relative loser industry with a bad reputation to the belle of the ball. Nothing better exemplifies this than the P/E of Microsoft.</p><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F94bdffc9-9ca2-40a3-bd6f-27fd7476c313_2400x1240.png"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F94bdffc9-9ca2-40a3-bd6f-27fd7476c313_2400x1240.png" width="1100" height="568" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/94bdffc9-9ca2-40a3-bd6f-27fd7476c313_2400x1240.png&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:568,&quot;width&quot;:1100,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt=""></a></figure></div><p>I don&#8217;t think we will get something this drastic in semis broadly - and if we do it&#8217;s already happening in the highest fliers of the space like Nvidia. But I find that the cyclical to secular thesis is still compelling. The same investors who hated Salesforce for making no meaningful FCF in 2012 are buying the shares hand over first in 2021. It might take that long - but I believe that will eventually be the case for semicap. </p><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F11dedac6-7d91-4e62-b74c-da0ca3450150_2400x1240.png"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F11dedac6-7d91-4e62-b74c-da0ca3450150_2400x1240.png" width="1100" height="568" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/11dedac6-7d91-4e62-b74c-da0ca3450150_2400x1240.png&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:568,&quot;width&quot;:1100,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt=""></a><figcaption class="image-caption">Nuts to think that AMAT / LRCX traded at a premium to Microsoft in 2013</figcaption></figure></div><p>Underlying these low multiples compared to the market is a financial model that works. These businesses have actually outperformed Microsoft with less modest multiple expansion - and obviously a bumpier ride. But if you believe that semis and semicap is a secular trend (I do), I think that investors will eventually appreciate these businesses for what they are - quasi-monopolies that are levered to the digitalization of our world. </p><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F8a297038-b2ab-4073-866a-247e2953ff66_2400x1240.png"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F8a297038-b2ab-4073-866a-247e2953ff66_2400x1240.png" width="1100" height="568" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/8a297038-b2ab-4073-866a-247e2953ff66_2400x1240.png&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:568,&quot;width&quot;:1100,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt=""></a></figure></div><p>A brief checkup on the positioning that they are under-owned in Long / Short TMT hedge funds means we have quite a while before they are loved. And that&#8217;s fine - the narrative comes after the results. </p><h2>Intel Mobileye Stub</h2><p>First I think it&#8217;s not very inspiring that Intel decided to do a public market equity stub of Mobileye. It&#8217;s reminiscent of VMWare, the former company that Pat Gelsinger led. The only difference here is that I would love to own Mobileye but would hate to own VMWare. So before dismissing the optically expensive $50 billion dollar headline - I want to dive a little deeper.  </p><p>Part of the process of an IPO is the elusive media leak. Intel leaks an IPO price to the press to generate a headline and tries to measure the reaction. That&#8217;s where the $50 billion dollar number comes from, Intel themselves. That price is the first level of negotiation where Intel throws out a really high offer and sees if anyone will bite.</p><p>Intel is trying to gauge if investors and the public will take a $50 billion dollar Mobileye seriously, and at first blush, it seemed hefty. Even given my extremely bullish stance on automotive semiconductors (<a href="https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/on-semi-and-nxpi-alchip-onto-and">I talk a bit more about it here</a>), that price seems insane. But I put my skepticism aside and made a simple comp sheet to see if Mobileye deserves the valuation. </p><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F6098cb92-9818-4012-ae3b-c00d3125867a_1209x501.png"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F6098cb92-9818-4012-ae3b-c00d3125867a_1209x501.png" width="1100" height="456" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/6098cb92-9818-4012-ae3b-c00d3125867a_1209x501.png&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:456,&quot;width&quot;:1100,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:60310,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt=""></a></figure></div><p>That $50 billion dollar valuation seems possible! Mobileye would trade at a hefty premium to other automotive semiconductor stocks, but given they have 100% revenue exposure instead of 30-40% I believe that&#8217;s justified. And if we were to compare Mobileye to the likes of Nvidia and Marvell, its growth and margins would be a premium but automotive exposure is scarce. I can buy $50 billion. So what does that mean for the value of Intel as a whole?</p><p>My first reaction to the news was Intel ex-Mobileye should be cheap as hell, but the more I dug the less impressed I became. The big first problem is what exactly is the earnings power of Intel in 2022? I can say with confidence I believe that the street is still too high - <a href="https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/intels-turnaround-plan-lam-research">I think they earn ~$3.20-3.40 a share</a> and consensus is still at ~$3.74 a share. The problem is that the revenue guidance is completely gone in the near term and we are just left with a long-term guide, and even then we were given &#8220;above 50% margins&#8221; but no further detail. That&#8217;s a lot of uncertainty - and your belief in a growing data center or consumer group with just a bit of margin lift can swing numbers +/- 10%. What I&#8217;m trying to say is that in order to have a view on the standalone Intel being cheap or not - you have to have a strong view of their numbers. I don&#8217;t have that. I attached my quick and dirty model so you can input assumptions yourself. </p><p>My stab at the numbers <strong>put Intel at just around 10x 2022 EBIT</strong> - which is pretty worrying. Something I&#8217;ve noticed is that when a company is in freefall it always seems to stick to a round number in whatever multiple is easiest to grasp to. EBITDA is utterly unforecastable, and EPS is going to have a litany of adjustments. I think ~10x is not a coincidence. </p><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb9df67c4-72a4-4d33-8f70-efea58333d8c_1056x574.png"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb9df67c4-72a4-4d33-8f70-efea58333d8c_1056x574.png" width="1056" height="574" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/b9df67c4-72a4-4d33-8f70-efea58333d8c_1056x574.png&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:574,&quot;width&quot;:1056,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:55049,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt=""></a></figure></div><p>In my experience, that round number is kind of worrying. I think of Stericycle - a company I refreshed the valuation on every 6 months from 2016 to 2019 and no matter what would happen the multiple would be at 11-12x EBITDA and EBITDA estimates, of course, were always too high. I think right now the direction of estimates is more important than multiple - and the 10x EBIT multiple doesn&#8217;t look that attractive to me. </p><p>Intel has traded for 10x EBIT in the past even without the Mobileye stake valued independently of Intel. Intel traded at 10x EBIT as recently as 2019 - and shares are essentially sideways since then. </p><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fe4f5ab53-9a81-41fa-afab-69a69233ee51_2400x1240.png"><img src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fe4f5ab53-9a81-41fa-afab-69a69233ee51_2400x1240.png" width="1100" height="568" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/e4f5ab53-9a81-41fa-afab-69a69233ee51_2400x1240.png&quot;,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:568,&quot;width&quot;:1100,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt=""></a></figure></div><p>I was hoping that Intel was either too cheap to pass (5-6x EBIT) but once again this is a hope trade. I still feel like it&#8217;s too early to catch the knife at Intel. I actually have become a lot more positive on the culture and execution but there is a lot of wood to chop, and I think when the signs that give you confidence in their turnaround do appear, you&#8217;ll maybe miss the first 20% but have more confidence to bet in size. </p><p>I think we are still in wait-and-see mode, and given how long it will take to ramp Intel Foundry Services, we have time to watch and wait. If you&#8217;re not satisfied with yourself - take a look at my attached model to tinker with the assumptions yourself. (Behind the paywall)</p><div><hr></div><p>That&#8217;s all for this week folks. I will hopefully have a 2022 outlook for ya&#8217;ll next week. Hope everyone is staying safe during these weird times. </p><div class="paywall-jump"></div><p></p><div class="file-embed-wrapper"><div class="file-embed-container-reader"><div class="file-embed-container-top"><image class="file-embed-thumbnail-default" src="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack.com%2Fimg%2Fattachment_icon.svg"></image><div class="file-embed-details"><div class="file-embed-details-h1">Intel Stub Model</div><div class="file-embed-details-h2">50.8KB &#8729; XLSX File</div></div><a class="file-embed-button wide" href="https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/api/v1/file/9d53bf64-b02a-4fa1-9356-0cc59e51bbfd.xlsx"><span class="file-embed-button-text">Download</span></a></div><a class="file-embed-button narrow" href="https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/api/v1/file/9d53bf64-b02a-4fa1-9356-0cc59e51bbfd.xlsx"><span class="file-embed-button-text">Download</span></a></div></div>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Semicon West Sparknotes]]></title><description><![CDATA[Some high level observations from Semicon West]]></description><link>https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/semicon-west-sparknotes</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/semicon-west-sparknotes</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Doug (mule)]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 13 Dec 2021 12:30:38 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/h_600,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffb852f62-dbdc-4200-82d4-eec1a73da099_1127x605.png" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[
      <p>
          <a href="https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/semicon-west-sparknotes">
              Read more
          </a>
      </p>
   ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Semicon West and Price Raise Notice]]></title><description><![CDATA[Final Reminder about the price raise]]></description><link>https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/semicon-west-and-price-raise-notice</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/semicon-west-and-price-raise-notice</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Doug (mule)]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 06 Dec 2021 12:00:57 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/34a51195-f3ae-4bd9-96a8-26488679ec3b_1500x500.png" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Hey everyone! I just wanted to make sure ya&#8217;ll know about today&#8217;s price increase. I will be raising the price of the paid subscription today. This is the final heads-up - and I&#8217;m giving you time if you didn&#8217;t know about it - the price raise will happen tonight at 10:00 pm PST and if you miss it just email me. <a href="https://www.fabricatedknowledge.com/p/the-rising-tide-of-semiconductor">I announced it two weeks ago in the post about rising semiconductor costs</a> (funny huh?) and have been tweeting quite a bit about it.</p><p><strong>The price raise summary is</strong> </p><ul><li><p>$20 a month to $30 dollars a month</p></li><li><p>$240 annually to $300 dollars annually</p></li></ul><p>As a reminder, current subscribers both monthly and annually are <strong>locked into their current prices</strong>. That means if you&#8217;re currently paying $20 a month, you will continue to pay $20 a month. I want to be clear about that - and give everyone who supported me thus far an opportunity to lock in the lower price. If you read this late - just reach out to me and let&#8217;s have a conversation.  </p><div><hr></div><h2>SEMICON West</h2><p>I&#8217;m headed to SEMICON West this week in San Francisco - and I love to meet up in person. If you&#8217;re there - give me a shout. If enough of ya&#8217;ll show interest I would love to do a happy hour with everyone. A mix of a Twitter and Substack meetup.</p><p>I&#8217;ll also be posting a summary post of SEMICON West and what I found meaningful on Thursday, so make sure to watch out for that. No paywall there - just coverage of some hopefully interesting events. </p><p>Otherwise, I hope you have a wonderful week and enjoy the holiday season with your family. Until next time! </p>]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>